<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Effective Altruism on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/effective-altruism/</link><description>Recent content in Effective Altruism on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.141.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 23:43:27 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/effective-altruism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>EAGxBerkeley: Thoughts and Reflections</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 23:43:27 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For context,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I don&amp;rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&amp;rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&amp;rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&amp;rsquo;ve been to, the
&lt;a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven&lt;/a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
</p>
<p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.</p>
<p>For context,</p>
<ol>
<li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.</li>
</ol>
<p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&rsquo;ve been to, the  
<a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven</a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!</p>
<p>My goal for the conference was mostly to network and to learn from other&rsquo;s how to best organize and run a local EA group, in my case  
<a href="https://effectivealtruismla.org/" target="_blank">EA Los Angeles</a>. On both of these fronts, I would say the conference was a huge success. Between the talks, the one-on-ones and the after-parties, I returned to my friend&rsquo;s place each evening bubbling with energy and eager to &ldquo;get to work&rdquo;!</p>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve had a few days to organize my notes and wanted to share a few takeaways (in no particular order):</p>
<ul>
<li>While there has been impressive progress in the past couple of years, cultivated meat still appears many years away from going &ldquo;mainstream&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>I still believe supply-side interventions (real cultivated meat at a comparable price point) is the most promising path to ending or dramatically reducing factory farming.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>AI safety / security, as a field or subfield, will only continue to receive more and more attention. ChatGPT o1 was released today for some additional context.
<ul>
<li>My guess is that over half of the attendees were there solely, or at least primarily, for AI safety.</li>
<li>This fields also seems to attract a lot of young, talented individuals, particularly from mathematics and computer-science backgrounds.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Much of the AI safety research is still highly theoretical.
<ul>
<li>This might be obvious (it is research after all) but part of me is eager to see a few AI safety orgs adopt a more engineering-focused approach. I think  
<a href="https://vitalik.eth.limo/general/2023/11/27/techno_optimism.html#dacc" target="_blank">Vitalik Buterin</a>&rsquo;s  
<a href="https://80000hours.org/podcast/episodes/vitalik-buterin-techno-optimism/" target="_blank">defensive acceleration</a> has a lot of merits.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In many ways, this conference felt like two simultaneous conferences, an AI-safety conference and a smaller, animal-welfare conference sharing the same venue.</li>
<li>One of my favorite talks was by Derek Shiller from Rethinking Priorities on &ldquo;Bargaining Approach to Moral Uncertainty&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>See previous bullet point about differences in priorities.</li>
<li>The topic gives <em>directionality</em>.</li>
<li>Check out  
<a href="https://parliament.rethinkpriorities.org" target="_blank">The Moral Parliament Tool</a></li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t think I have fully digested the three previous bullets&hellip;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I sat for the guided meditation on Sunday morning and was glad to see it on the schedule.
<ul>
<li>Reduce suffering through practice?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This list far from comprehensive but hopefully highlights a few of the ideas and <em>vibes</em> that I picked up at the conferences. There were many talks I was unfortunately unable to attend but I look forward to catching when they are posted on YouTube.</p>
<p>This conference was a wonderful showing for the community, and community is nothing more than people hanging out and enjoying each other&rsquo;s company! It&rsquo;s even more encouraging to be part of a community that is genuinely focused on making the world a better place.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>