<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Kubernetes on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/kubernetes/</link><description>Recent content in Kubernetes on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.143.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/kubernetes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>eskild.art: building for the future</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on
&lt;a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&amp;rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django&lt;/a> with
&lt;a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS&lt;/a> using Postgres deployed on Google&amp;rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.</em></p>
<h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack</h2>
<p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on  
<a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art</a>, and I&rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.</p>
<p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running  
<a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django</a> with  
<a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS</a> using Postgres deployed on Google&rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://x.com/dexhorthy/status/856639005462417409" target="_blank">It&rsquo;s certainly amusing</a> to see a basic web app deployed on a compute environment which is orders of magnitude more expensive than the previous environment. However, I wanted to take this opportunity to brush up on Kubernetes and GCP while leaving room to growth. Who knows, maybe one day I&rsquo;ll deploying it on the Kubernetes cluster running on my  
<a href="https://eskild.blog/posts/2024-08-27-hl0/" target="_blank">homelab</a> ;)</p>
<p>I chose Django because it has many great features &ldquo;out-of-the-box,&rdquo; such as the admin panel and because I resonate with their slogan: &ldquo;The web framework for perfectionists with deadlines.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="coding-with-ai">Coding with AI</h2>
<p>Going from an empty repo to a simple site deployed on GKE in less than three weeks is moderately impressive. That said, considering this was something I hacked on a few hours here and there, I quite pleased.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m being honest with myself, this is something I don&rsquo;t think I could&rsquo;ve accomplished in this timeframe without the assistance of AI tools like  
<a href="https://www.cursor.com/" target="_blank">Cursor</a> and  
<a href="https://chatgpt.com/" target="_blank">ChatGPT</a> (o1). In fact, if I had to guess, I would say that about 90% of the code was AI-generated.</p>
<p>While I think tools like these are revolutionizing the software engineering field, I suspect it would&rsquo;ve taken someone without development experience quite a bit longer, mainly because the infrastructure setup and app deployment can be confusing and a bit intimidating. Getting a local Django app up and running was the easy part.</p>
<p>Cursor is one of the most impressive AI tools out there, but it&rsquo;s certainly not perfect. If you&rsquo;re not paying attention, it will add unnecessary files and duplicate existing functionality; hallucinations (or rather confabulations) are problems I don&rsquo;t see getting fully resolved anytime soon.</p>
<p>In general, these tools works best if you have a basic idea of what you&rsquo;re doing. And as the codebase become more complex, these AI tools tend to require more guidance and specialized prompting.</p>
<p>Besides speed-to-market and other business metrics, this experience has me wondering whether security and reliability will be some of the key differentiators going forward. We will likely see a lot more apps deployed by non-developers in the coming years but I suspect once their app start gaining traction, professional developers will come in and ensure the site can scale, is reliable and adheres to security best practices.</p>
<h2 id="wrap-up">Wrap up</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! I hope you enjoy the challenges and the art!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>