<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Tree of the Month on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/tree-of-the-month/</link><description>Recent content in Tree of the Month on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.140.2</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:39:37 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/tree-of-the-month/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Giant Sequoia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:39:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson&lt;/a> on &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000"></p>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.</p>
<p>There are species of trees that thrive in this fiery environment, one such tree is the Giant Sequoia.</p>
<p>Giant Sequoias hold the record for the largest tree by volume, specifically  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/seki/learn/nature/largest-trees-in-world.htm" target="_blank">General Sherman</a> with a trunk volume of over 1,480 cubic meters (52,500 cubic feet). They can grow up to 85 meters (280 feet) tall, and their gorgeous red-brown bark can grow up to 60 centimeters (24 inches) thick. The thickness of their bark, and lack of flammable sap, make these mature Giant Sequoias resistant to most fires.</p>
<p>The reproductive process of the Giant Sequoia and forest fires are intimately linked. The cones of the Giant Sequoia are serotinous, meaning they require an external trigger — in this case, fire — to release their seeds. The heat of the raging forest fire causes these tightly sealed cones to dry out and open up, setting their seeds free. With the cleared forest floor and a fresh layer of nutrient-rich ash, these seeds have an opportunity to germinate and become the next generation of Giant Sequoias.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re up close to a mature Giant Sequoia, you can often see the scars of past fires. You might be comforted knowing their offspring may be nearby</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_fire_art.jpg" alt=" A painting of the bark of a Giant Sequoia that looks like fire." width="500"></p>
<p>As I write this, I reflect on the ideas of resilience, adaptation, and creative destruction in the broadest sense. It&rsquo;s August 2023, and some tangible form of AI is already here. Are humans like the Giant Sequoias, ready to use this power to our advantage, and to grow and develop beyond our current capabilities? Or are we like the old and dying underbrush that is about to be burnt away to make way for a new form of life?</p>
<p>Or is my analogy being stretched too far? Either way, I can&rsquo;t help but feel a sense of uncertainty about the future, a mixture of both anxiety and excitement.</p>
<p>Our ancestors harnessed the power of fire and it has been the stuff of legend ever since. It unlocked even greater opportunities for humanity and fair to say that fire has been a net positive even factoring in its destructive nature <sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence is humanity&rsquo;s newest fire! A fire that listens, speaks and creates. Some of the dangers of artificial intelligence are easy to imagine, more fake news and increased surveillance, while understanding the potential existential dangers requires a robust definition of intelligence and a basic understanding of  
<a href="https://www.alignmentforum.org/" target="_blank">the alignment problem</a>.</p>
<p>Just as the immediate dangers are easy to imagine and the truly catastrophic ones difficult to pin down, the same pattern holds for the benefits of AI. The immediate benefits of AI are here already, a personal tutorial at your fingertips and the ability to generate new content with a faction of the effort. The truly awesome changes are difficult to predict.</p>
<p>Innovations as large and sweeping as the harnessing of fire, the invention of the atomic bomb or the creation of artificial intelligence force humanity to adapt to them in fundamental ways. Will AI burn too hot and destroy the entire forest, including the mighty Giant Sequoias? Will it usher in a new era of growth and prosperity? Or will it be regulated in such a way that it&rsquo;s rendered useless?</p>
<p>Thirty years from now, we will likely know how this has played out but until then, prepare for change and try to have fun with it!</p>
<p><sup>1</sup>
One possible way that the harnessing of fire might lead to the extinction of life on Earth (a net negative) is via the nuclear bomb, the ultimate expression of fire.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Joshua Tree</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 15:09:04 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
&lt;p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)&lt;/a>.
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park&lt;/a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself &lt;sup>
&lt;a href="#references">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
<p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)</a>.  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park</a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.</p>
<p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself <sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>All living organisms – including humans of course – are highly dependent on their environment and other organisms for survival; the Joshua Tree is no different. For the Joshua Tree to reproduce, it requires a unique set of weather conditions, as well as assistance from a few local species.</p>
<p>First, the Joshua Tree requires a winter freeze and a timely spring rainfall. These conditions alone inhibit the tree, and many other desert plants, from blossoming every year.</p>
<p>Once the tree does blossom, the flowers are pollinated by a single species, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prodoxidae" target="_blank">yucca moth</a>. These two species have come to a mostly mutually beneficial relationship whereby, in exchange for pollinating the Joshua Tree flowers, the yucca moth is permitted to lay her eggs inside the flower ovary. Not only do the eggs benefit from some level of protection, but the larvae also feed on the Joshua Tree seeds when they eventually hatch.</p>
<p>If enough seeds remain, the next act, though still not fully understood by scientists, seems to depend on the assistance of desert rodents such as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-tailed_antelope_squirrel" target="_blank">white-tail antelope squirrel</a>. By storing the Joshua Tree seeds in nearby, underground caches – often under the shade and protection of other desert shrubs such as the Blackbush – these squirrels offer the Joshua tree an increased chance that their seeds will germinate <sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Even if all these conditions are met, the chances of a seed germinating and growing to adolescence are still quite slim. Factor in the changing climate and the potential need for the Joshua Tree species to migrate to more suitable environments, and it&rsquo;s no wonder that the outlook of these trees is unfortunately bleak.</p>
<p>As individuals, there are changes we can make to reduce the negative impacts of climate change and to improve the odds that the Joshua Tree makes it to the 22nd century. Yet given the scope of the problem, large-scale societal changes will need to be enacted, and enacted soon.</p>
<p>However, we can honor the Joshua Tree, yucca moth, and the other desert species by recognizing our reliance on the environment, on other species and on one another. Doing so might make us more compassionate and remind us that our “successes” and our “failures” are not entirely our own.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup> Waitman, B. A., et al. “Seed Dispersal and Seed Fate in Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia).” Journal of Arid Environments, vol. 81, 2012, pp. 1–8. Crossref, doi:10.1016/j.jaridenv.2011.12.012.
<br>
<sup>2</sup> Jones, Taylor and Goldrick, Sabrina,  
<a href="https://pdf.wildearthguardians.org/site/DocServer/Joshua_tree_petition.pdf?docID=16684" target="_blank">Petition to List the Joshua Tree (Yucca brevifolia) Under the Endangered Species Act</a>, 28 Sept 2015.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Southern Magnolia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 15:07:29 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Photo by
&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
<p><sup>Photo by  
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner</a></sup></p>
<p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.</p>
<p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.</p>
<p>However, one characteristic of trees not often discussed is their astonishing aesthetic beauty.</p>
<p>One such tree commonly planted for its splendor is the Magnolia tree and in particular, the Southern Magnolia (Magnolia Grandiflora).</p>
<p>This gorgeous evergreen can grow up to 30 meters (~90 feet) tall with a canopy that can potentially grow just as wide. Beloved in part for their large, white fragrant flowers, these trees grow natively in the south-eastern United States but have been planted across the country due to their popularity.</p>
<p>Across southern California, there are streets lined, and parks filled with these wonderful shade trees. For instance, there sits an enormous Southern Magnolia in the main park in my mom’s hometown, and when I see it, it puts a smile on my face for no other reason than its size and beauty.</p>
<p>Growing up, what distinguished magnolias from other trees, was first and foremost their large, waxy, oval-shaped leaves. Sure, there are other trees with leaves as large or larger, consider the maple leaf, but I can’t think of another tree with leaves as thick or as hardy as those from the Southern Magnolia.</p>
<p>Even though it was one of just a few trees that I could identify as a child, it wasn’t until a few years ago that I started to appreciate their true beauty. It’s not only a beauty that is perceived through my eyes and other sense but also one that is understood more intrinsically.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Grandmother's Valencia Orange Tree</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 14:59:24 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/orange_tree_single.jpg" alt="A single orange dangling from its stem" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I catch a familiar scent of orange blossom as I walk around my neighborhood, a scent I can’t help but associate with spring and summer at my grandma’s house.&lt;/p>
&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/orange_tree_sky.jpg" alt="A view of the top of the orange tree and the blue sky" width="500">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spent nearly every childhood summer at her place, a reprieve from having spent the previous ten, much colder, months in northern Europe. Her orange tree represented the hot California sun, with oranges the color to match.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_single.jpg" alt="A single orange dangling from its stem" width="1000"></p>
<p>I catch a familiar scent of orange blossom as I walk around my neighborhood, a scent I can’t help but associate with spring and summer at my grandma’s house.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_sky.jpg" alt="A view of the top of the orange tree and the blue sky" width="500"></p>
<p>I spent nearly every childhood summer at her place, a reprieve from having spent the previous ten, much colder, months in northern Europe. Her orange tree represented the hot California sun, with oranges the color to match.</p>
<p>A tall glass of her hand-squeezed orange juice on a hot and dry summer day rejuvenates the body with every sweet and delightful sip. A sweeter or juicier orange simply does not exist.</p>
<p>This vibrant  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valencia_orange" target="_blank">Valencia Orange Tree</a> is a fixture of my grandma’s house, as much as her 70’s era wood-paneled eastern wall is to her living room. And I’m so grateful she hasn’t torn the tree out, the unfortunate trend of many southern California homeowners.</p>
<p>My grandma’s orange tree has dependably provided oranges – and at times, other grafted citruses – for over six decades and is still going strong. And my grandma has dependably provided for her family – in all the traditionally unromantic ways – for just as long and, at nearly 85, still does what she can.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_inside.jpg" alt="A view of the inside of the orange tree" width="500"></p>
<p>I am learning a lesson from my grandma and her orange tree. A lesson in dependability and what it means to provide for others without asking for anything in return.</p>
<p>Throughout my life, I have probably slept more nights at my grandma’s house than anywhere else. And although my grandma and I haven’t always seen eye to eye, she has always been ready to provide for those in need. It’s in her nature, just as it’s the nature of an orange tree to blossom in the spring and fruit oranges in the summer.</p>
<p>If and when I get to her age, I hope to look back on my life knowing I was as trustworthy and dependable. That I provided for those that I love without doing so out of some sense of obligation or as part of some formal transaction.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for all that she has done for everyone and for all the good memories her house and her tree have enabled.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 14:50:42 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/bristlecone_pine_unsplash.jpg" alt="A large bristlecone-pine on the side of a rocky hill" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;sup>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine in the White Mountains (CA) photo by
&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@stp_com" target="_blank">Tim Peterson&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scattered atop a few of the high mountains of California, Nevada and Utah, sits an extremely special tree, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinus_longaeva" target="_blank">Great Basin Bristlecone Pine (Pinus longaeva)&lt;/a>. Rooted in rocky and dry soil, they grow slowly and in isolation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Widely considered one of the longest-lived sexually reproducing, non-clonal organisms on earth, their long lifecycle has been instrumental to the scientific community.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/bristlecone_pine_unsplash.jpg" alt="A large bristlecone-pine on the side of a rocky hill" width="1000"></p>
<p><sup>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine in the White Mountains (CA) photo by  
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@stp_com" target="_blank">Tim Peterson</a></sup></p>
<p>Scattered atop a few of the high mountains of California, Nevada and Utah, sits an extremely special tree, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinus_longaeva" target="_blank">Great Basin Bristlecone Pine (Pinus longaeva)</a>. Rooted in rocky and dry soil, they grow slowly and in isolation.</p>
<p>Widely considered one of the longest-lived sexually reproducing, non-clonal organisms on earth, their long lifecycle has been instrumental to the scientific community.</p>
<p>Due to the long lifespan of individual trees, and how extraordinarily slow their dead wood decays, scientists have been able to construct a continuous tree-ring chronology. This is done by comparing tree-ring samples from several different trees, both dead and alive, with the current chronology dating back over 9000 years <sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/dendrochronology.jpg" alt="Diagram explaining how tree rings from different trees match up to create a timeline" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Constructing a continuous tree-ring chronology (see  
<a href="https://archaeologymuseum.ca/dendrochronology-tree-ring-dating/" target="_blank">Museum of Ontario Archaeology</a>)</sup></p>
<p>This process is known as  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dendrochronology" target="_blank">dendrochronology</a> and has been vital in helping us understand the changes in climate and atmospheric conditions through the years. These insights have also been used to  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiocarbon_dating#Calibration" target="_blank">recalibrate the C-14 radiocarbon</a> dating process, helping archaeologists more precisely sketch out the timeline of the past.</p>
<p>Many of the discoveries and insights have only been made in the past few decades. How many more secrets do these Bristlecone Pines hold? And now consider the countless other tree species and the lessons they have yet to impart.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/bristlecone_pine_twisting.jpg" alt="A twisted bristlecone-pine branch against a blue sky" width="350"></p>
<p>Getting to see these warped and distorted giants up close forced me to reflect on how much the human species has accomplished in the lifespan of just a single tree.</p>
<p>Take  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methuselah_%28tree%29" target="_blank">Methuselah</a>, for instance, the namesake of the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methuselah" target="_blank">longest-living biblical character</a> and a tree  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dating_the_Bible" target="_blank">older than the bible</a> itself. This particular tree is estimated to be around 4,850 years old and holds the record for the oldest living tree <sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>For scale, Methuselah had already begun taking root around the time the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Pyramid_of_Giza" target="_blank">Great Pyramids of Giza</a> were being constructed, when the human population is estimated to be less than 27 million the world over. Just pause for a moment to consider how much the planet has changed and how far we have come as a species in that time<sup> 
<a href="#references">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Some might argue that the incredible progress we’ve made thus far will invariably continue while others argue that nothing in the past few centuries has fundamentally changed and point to all the problems in the world as evidence.</p>
<p>From my perspective, we have made immense and undeniable progress in the sciences and technology, and in the strengths of our institutions which attempt to embody our values and ideals. But if the past few years have demonstrated anything, it’s that we have much work to do.</p>
<p>We are living in a unique moment in history, at the elbow of an exponential curve of progress and abundance, but it’s important to remember that our actions and decisions today will be felt far into the future.</p>
<p>We might do well to take a lesson from these ancient sentinels, a species that has traded speed for longevity.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup>
Miller, Leonard. “Dendrochronology.” <em>The Ancient Bristlecone Pine</em>,  
<a href="http://www.sonic.net/bristlecone/dendro.html" target="_blank">www.sonic.net/bristlecone/dendro.html</a>.</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
Brown PhD, Peter. “RMTRR OLDLIST.” <em>Rocky Mountain Tree-Ring Research</em>,  
<a href="http://www.rmtrr.org/oldlist.htm" target="_blank">www.rmtrr.org/oldlist.htm</a>.</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>
McEvedy, Colin and Richard Jones, 1978, &ldquo;Atlas of World Population History,&rdquo; Facts on File, New York, pp. 342-351.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Big Berried Manzanita</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 14:44:05 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail&lt;/a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000"></p>
<p><sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)</sup></p>
<p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail</a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/pinnacles_nps.jpg" alt="A view of the rock formations in Pinnacles National Park" width="1000"></p>
<p>It was the distinct, metallic-like, red bark that first drew our attention and our instant admiration.</p>
<p>I felt compelled to research this tree – what I would come to know as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">Big Berried Manzanita (Arctostaphylos glauca)</a> – and this is exactly what I did when I got home.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_bark.jpg" alt="A close up of the metallic-looking bark of the manzanita tree" width="500"></p>
<p>Technically more of a large shrub than a tree, these striking evergreen plants are native to the chaparral regions of California and Baja California and have evolved an extraordinary robustness. They grow well in acidic soils, are resistant to heat, drought and cold, and can live up to 100 years<sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As their name suggests, the Big Berried Manzanitas are known for their relatively large, red berries and this is what distinguishes them from other manzanita species.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_berries.jpg" alt="A close up of the red manzanita berries" width="500"></p>
<p><sup> 
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">“Arctostaphylos glauca“</a> by  
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Stan_Shebs" target="_blank">Stan Shebs</a> is licensed under  
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="_blank">CC BY 3.0</a></sup></p>
<p>The general term, manzanita, comes to us from the Spanish who thought the red berries resembled little red apples; the Spanish diminutive of &ldquo;manzana&rdquo; or apple.</p>
<p>These Big Berried Manzanita can reach heights of up to 6 meters or 20 feet tall, decorated with beautiful blue-green, oval leaves. Although I didn&rsquo;t bring my handy measuring tape with me, I was able to stand comfortably beneath the twisting branches to admire their bark.</p>
<p>A simply wonderful tree.</p>
<p>This trip reminded me of the importance of slowing down. And that the simple pleasures in life – the warmth of a campfire, the exhilaration of moving my body and the enjoyment of an honest conversation with a friend – are some of the best pleasures in life.</p>
<p>My roommate and I remain extremely grateful for the whole experience. We not only discovered the gorgeous manzanita tree, but as we sat to admire the beautiful pastel-colored rocks, we were fortunate enough to witness the majestic condor soar effortlessly overhead.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/soaring_condor_nps.jpg" alt="A soaring condor overhead" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Soaring Condor (NPS/Mason Cummings)</sup></p>
<p>I hope this series inspires you, dear reader, to get out and discover for yourself the wonders of our natural world. I will conclude with a quote from legendary naturalist John Muir<sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The clearest way into the Universe is through a forest wilderness.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup>
Howard, Janet L. “Arctostaphylos Glauca.” Fire Effects Information System, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory, 1993,  
<a href="https://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html" target="_blank">www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html</a> [broken link].</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
Muir, John, and Linnie Marsh Wolfe. <em>John of the Mountains: The Unpublished Journals of John Muir</em>. University of Wisconsin Press, Madison, 1979.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Introducing the Tree of the Month series</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 14:42:16 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/beautiful_woodland_path.jpg" alt="A beautiful woodland path" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/beautiful_woodland_path.jpg" alt="A beautiful woodland path" width="1000"></p>
<p>Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.</p>
<p>To honor our important friends, once a month for the year 2021, I will share a post on a specific tree I find fascinating or have recently discovered myself. Some trees will be familiar to most, some trees might only be appreciated by scientists working closely with them. All of them will inspire awe and appreciation.</p>
<p>The explicit goals of this series are to introduce myself to more fascinating and beautiful trees while sharing my excitement with others. My wish is for trees, and our natural environment more broadly, to be looked upon with a set of fresh eyes, and fundamentally respected for all their forgotten benefits.</p>
<p>As far as I am aware, there exists not a tree in the universe besides here on Earth. As the species with the greatest ability to affect our surroundings, we ought to take better care of the trees, so they can take care of all of us.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>