<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>National Park Service on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/national-park-service/</link><description>Recent content in National Park Service on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.142.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 15:09:04 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/national-park-service/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Joshua Tree</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 15:09:04 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
&lt;p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)&lt;/a>.
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park&lt;/a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself &lt;sup>
&lt;a href="#references">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
<p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)</a>.  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park</a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.</p>
<p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself <sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>All living organisms – including humans of course – are highly dependent on their environment and other organisms for survival; the Joshua Tree is no different. For the Joshua Tree to reproduce, it requires a unique set of weather conditions, as well as assistance from a few local species.</p>
<p>First, the Joshua Tree requires a winter freeze and a timely spring rainfall. These conditions alone inhibit the tree, and many other desert plants, from blossoming every year.</p>
<p>Once the tree does blossom, the flowers are pollinated by a single species, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prodoxidae" target="_blank">yucca moth</a>. These two species have come to a mostly mutually beneficial relationship whereby, in exchange for pollinating the Joshua Tree flowers, the yucca moth is permitted to lay her eggs inside the flower ovary. Not only do the eggs benefit from some level of protection, but the larvae also feed on the Joshua Tree seeds when they eventually hatch.</p>
<p>If enough seeds remain, the next act, though still not fully understood by scientists, seems to depend on the assistance of desert rodents such as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-tailed_antelope_squirrel" target="_blank">white-tail antelope squirrel</a>. By storing the Joshua Tree seeds in nearby, underground caches – often under the shade and protection of other desert shrubs such as the Blackbush – these squirrels offer the Joshua tree an increased chance that their seeds will germinate <sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Even if all these conditions are met, the chances of a seed germinating and growing to adolescence are still quite slim. Factor in the changing climate and the potential need for the Joshua Tree species to migrate to more suitable environments, and it&rsquo;s no wonder that the outlook of these trees is unfortunately bleak.</p>
<p>As individuals, there are changes we can make to reduce the negative impacts of climate change and to improve the odds that the Joshua Tree makes it to the 22nd century. Yet given the scope of the problem, large-scale societal changes will need to be enacted, and enacted soon.</p>
<p>However, we can honor the Joshua Tree, yucca moth, and the other desert species by recognizing our reliance on the environment, on other species and on one another. Doing so might make us more compassionate and remind us that our “successes” and our “failures” are not entirely our own.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup> Waitman, B. A., et al. “Seed Dispersal and Seed Fate in Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia).” Journal of Arid Environments, vol. 81, 2012, pp. 1–8. Crossref, doi:10.1016/j.jaridenv.2011.12.012.
<br>
<sup>2</sup> Jones, Taylor and Goldrick, Sabrina,  
<a href="https://pdf.wildearthguardians.org/site/DocServer/Joshua_tree_petition.pdf?docID=16684" target="_blank">Petition to List the Joshua Tree (Yucca brevifolia) Under the Endangered Species Act</a>, 28 Sept 2015.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Big Berried Manzanita</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 14:44:05 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail&lt;/a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000"></p>
<p><sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)</sup></p>
<p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail</a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/pinnacles_nps.jpg" alt="A view of the rock formations in Pinnacles National Park" width="1000"></p>
<p>It was the distinct, metallic-like, red bark that first drew our attention and our instant admiration.</p>
<p>I felt compelled to research this tree – what I would come to know as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">Big Berried Manzanita (Arctostaphylos glauca)</a> – and this is exactly what I did when I got home.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_bark.jpg" alt="A close up of the metallic-looking bark of the manzanita tree" width="500"></p>
<p>Technically more of a large shrub than a tree, these striking evergreen plants are native to the chaparral regions of California and Baja California and have evolved an extraordinary robustness. They grow well in acidic soils, are resistant to heat, drought and cold, and can live up to 100 years<sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As their name suggests, the Big Berried Manzanitas are known for their relatively large, red berries and this is what distinguishes them from other manzanita species.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_berries.jpg" alt="A close up of the red manzanita berries" width="500"></p>
<p><sup> 
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">“Arctostaphylos glauca“</a> by  
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Stan_Shebs" target="_blank">Stan Shebs</a> is licensed under  
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="_blank">CC BY 3.0</a></sup></p>
<p>The general term, manzanita, comes to us from the Spanish who thought the red berries resembled little red apples; the Spanish diminutive of &ldquo;manzana&rdquo; or apple.</p>
<p>These Big Berried Manzanita can reach heights of up to 6 meters or 20 feet tall, decorated with beautiful blue-green, oval leaves. Although I didn&rsquo;t bring my handy measuring tape with me, I was able to stand comfortably beneath the twisting branches to admire their bark.</p>
<p>A simply wonderful tree.</p>
<p>This trip reminded me of the importance of slowing down. And that the simple pleasures in life – the warmth of a campfire, the exhilaration of moving my body and the enjoyment of an honest conversation with a friend – are some of the best pleasures in life.</p>
<p>My roommate and I remain extremely grateful for the whole experience. We not only discovered the gorgeous manzanita tree, but as we sat to admire the beautiful pastel-colored rocks, we were fortunate enough to witness the majestic condor soar effortlessly overhead.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/soaring_condor_nps.jpg" alt="A soaring condor overhead" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Soaring Condor (NPS/Mason Cummings)</sup></p>
<p>I hope this series inspires you, dear reader, to get out and discover for yourself the wonders of our natural world. I will conclude with a quote from legendary naturalist John Muir<sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The clearest way into the Universe is through a forest wilderness.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup>
Howard, Janet L. “Arctostaphylos Glauca.” Fire Effects Information System, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory, 1993,  
<a href="https://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html" target="_blank">www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html</a> [broken link].</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
Muir, John, and Linnie Marsh Wolfe. <em>John of the Mountains: The Unpublished Journals of John Muir</em>. University of Wisconsin Press, Madison, 1979.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>