<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Aesthetics on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/aesthetics/</link><description>Recent content in Aesthetics on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.148.2</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 21:44:57 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/aesthetics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>eskild.art: going live</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-07-30-art/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 21:44:57 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-07-30-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art&lt;/a> is now live!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have plenty of ideas on what this might morph into but for now, it&amp;rsquo;s simply a gallery.
Can you solve the riddle to view the image?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> 
<a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art</a> is now live!</p>
<p>I have plenty of ideas on what this might morph into but for now, it&rsquo;s simply a gallery.
Can you solve the riddle to view the image?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Southern Magnolia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 15:07:29 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Photo by
&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
<p><sup>Photo by  
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner</a></sup></p>
<p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.</p>
<p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.</p>
<p>However, one characteristic of trees not often discussed is their astonishing aesthetic beauty.</p>
<p>One such tree commonly planted for its splendor is the Magnolia tree and in particular, the Southern Magnolia (Magnolia Grandiflora).</p>
<p>This gorgeous evergreen can grow up to 30 meters (~90 feet) tall with a canopy that can potentially grow just as wide. Beloved in part for their large, white fragrant flowers, these trees grow natively in the south-eastern United States but have been planted across the country due to their popularity.</p>
<p>Across southern California, there are streets lined, and parks filled with these wonderful shade trees. For instance, there sits an enormous Southern Magnolia in the main park in my mom’s hometown, and when I see it, it puts a smile on my face for no other reason than its size and beauty.</p>
<p>Growing up, what distinguished magnolias from other trees, was first and foremost their large, waxy, oval-shaped leaves. Sure, there are other trees with leaves as large or larger, consider the maple leaf, but I can’t think of another tree with leaves as thick or as hardy as those from the Southern Magnolia.</p>
<p>Even though it was one of just a few trees that I could identify as a child, it wasn’t until a few years ago that I started to appreciate their true beauty. It’s not only a beauty that is perceived through my eyes and other sense but also one that is understood more intrinsically.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>