<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Artificial Intelligence on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/</link><description>Recent content in Artificial Intelligence on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 17:00:17 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What's your humor setting Co-Pilot?</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 17:00:17 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</guid><description>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services, ChatGPT Plus and GitHub&amp;#39;s Co-Pilot but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &amp;ldquo;co-pilot&amp;rdquo; perfectly captures the current relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.
Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/copilot_humor_setting.jpg" alt="Meme from interstellar" width="1000">
<p>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services,  
<a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt-plus" target="_blank">ChatGPT Plus</a> and  
<a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" target="_blank">GitHub&#39;s Co-Pilot</a> but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo; perfectly captures the <em>current</em> relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.</p>
<p>Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing. As I began to type out <code>url = &quot;https://</code>, Co-Pilot generated a suggestion that I could accept by hitting tab. At this point, it didn&rsquo;t matter what the URL was so I accepted the suggestion. Any guesses what the URL was for? What if I told you it was for a YouTube video?</p>
<p>If you guessed, Rick Astley&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ">&ldquo;Never Gonna Give You Up&rdquo; music video</a>, you would be correct. I got  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rickrolling" target="_blank">rickrolled</a> by my Co-Pilot, damn!</p>
<hr>
<p>Without going into too much detail on how these Large Language Models (LLMs) work, it&rsquo;s important to know that these LLMs are trained on billions and billions of lines of text data from online sources including blogs, forums, and digitized books, just to name a few.  What this means is that a large fraction of all the entertaining, beautiful, mean, hopeful, hateful, weird and wonderful things we have collectively written, have been internalized by these LLMs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not a huge surprise that a URL generated by Co-Pilot would be one of the most famous internet memes. I would guess it&rsquo;s among the top 5 common URLs found in the &ldquo;wild&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This experience has once again highlighted that interacting with these LLMs - at least at this point in their development - is like interacting with a mirror of humanity. Training these large models on our collective knowledge has proven that, when concentrated in one entity like GPT4, it has the potential to reflect the vast spectrum of human behavior and culture, both the profound and the trivial.</p>
<p>As AI continues to evolve, the line between tool and collaborator will become increasingly blurred. Today, we might see AI as a &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo;, but in the future, these systems could become more akin to partners in our creative and professional endeavors. Or perhaps AIs could dispense with the need for a human &ldquo;pilot&rdquo; altogether.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of the previous two paragraphs were completed for my by ChatGPT using the previous paragraphs as the prompt.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I will conclude by encouraging folks who create content - practically speaking, everyone - to think twice before spreading lies, hate, or any other less-than-flattering ideas that will eventually be picked up by future LLMs; we should strive to ensure the best version of humanity is captured in the future training data sets.</p>
<p>If  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning_from_human_feedback" target="_blank">reinforcement learning with human feedback</a> (RLHF) is like scolding a child who swears, then improving the training dataset is akin to not swearing in front of the child to begin with.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s not swear in front of the AI.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Giant Sequoia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:39:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</guid><description>Photo by Nils Rasmusson on Unsplash
Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000"></p>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.</p>
<p>There are species of trees that thrive in this fiery environment, one such tree is the Giant Sequoia.</p>
<p>Giant Sequoias hold the record for the largest tree by volume, specifically  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/seki/learn/nature/largest-trees-in-world.htm" target="_blank">General Sherman</a> with a trunk volume of over 1,480 cubic meters (52,500 cubic feet). They can grow up to 85 meters (280 feet) tall, and their gorgeous red-brown bark can grow up to 60 centimeters (24 inches) thick. The thickness of their bark, and lack of flammable sap, make these mature Giant Sequoias resistant to most fires.</p>
<p>The reproductive process of the Giant Sequoia and forest fires are intimately linked. The cones of the Giant Sequoia are serotinous, meaning they require an external trigger — in this case, fire — to release their seeds. The heat of the raging forest fire causes these tightly sealed cones to dry out and open up, setting their seeds free. With the cleared forest floor and a fresh layer of nutrient-rich ash, these seeds have an opportunity to germinate and become the next generation of Giant Sequoias.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re up close to a mature Giant Sequoia, you can often see the scars of past fires. You might be comforted knowing their offspring may be nearby</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_fire_art.jpg" alt=" A painting of the bark of a Giant Sequoia that looks like fire." width="500"></p>
<p>As I write this, I reflect on the ideas of resilience, adaptation, and creative destruction in the broadest sense. It&rsquo;s August 2023, and some tangible form of AI is already here. Are humans like the Giant Sequoias, ready to use this power to our advantage, and to grow and develop beyond our current capabilities? Or are we like the old and dying underbrush that is about to be burnt away to make way for a new form of life?</p>
<p>Or is my analogy being stretched too far? Either way, I can&rsquo;t help but feel a sense of uncertainty about the future, a mixture of both anxiety and excitement.</p>
<p>Our ancestors harnessed the power of fire and it has been the stuff of legend ever since. It unlocked even greater opportunities for humanity and fair to say that fire has been a net positive even factoring in its destructive nature <sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence is humanity&rsquo;s newest fire! A fire that listens, speaks and creates. Some of the dangers of artificial intelligence are easy to imagine, more fake news and increased surveillance, while understanding the potential existential dangers requires a robust definition of intelligence and a basic understanding of  
<a href="https://www.alignmentforum.org/" target="_blank">the alignment problem</a>.</p>
<p>Just as the immediate dangers are easy to imagine and the truly catastrophic ones difficult to pin down, the same pattern holds for the benefits of AI. The immediate benefits of AI are here already, a personal tutorial at your fingertips and the ability to generate new content with a faction of the effort. The truly awesome changes are difficult to predict.</p>
<p>Innovations as large and sweeping as the harnessing of fire, the invention of the atomic bomb or the creation of artificial intelligence force humanity to adapt to them in fundamental ways. Will AI burn too hot and destroy the entire forest, including the mighty Giant Sequoias? Will it usher in a new era of growth and prosperity? Or will it be regulated in such a way that it&rsquo;s rendered useless?</p>
<p>Thirty years from now, we will likely know how this has played out but until then, prepare for change and try to have fun with it!</p>
<p><sup>1</sup>
One possible way that the harnessing of fire might lead to the extinction of life on Earth (a net negative) is via the nuclear bomb, the ultimate expression of fire.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>