<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Artificial Intelligence on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/</link><description>Recent content in Artificial Intelligence on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.140.2</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>eskild.art: building for the future</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on
&lt;a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&amp;rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django&lt;/a> with
&lt;a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS&lt;/a> using Postgres deployed on Google&amp;rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.</em></p>
<h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack</h2>
<p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on  
<a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art</a>, and I&rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.</p>
<p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running  
<a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django</a> with  
<a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS</a> using Postgres deployed on Google&rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://x.com/dexhorthy/status/856639005462417409" target="_blank">It&rsquo;s certainly amusing</a> to see a basic web app deployed on a compute environment that is literally four orders of magnitude more expensive than the previous environment. That said, I wanted to take this opportunity to brush up on Kubernetes and GCP while leaving room to grow. I chose Django because it has many great features &ldquo;out-of-the-box,&rdquo; such as the admin panel and the ability to add new apps quickly; I resonate with their slogan: &ldquo;The web framework for perfectionists with deadlines.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="coding-with-ai">Coding with AI</h2>
<p>Going from an empty repo to a live site deployed on GKE in less than three weeks is impressive! It&rsquo;s especially impressive considering this was something I hacked on a few hours here and there as I spent most of my holiday break visiting family and friends. If I&rsquo;m being honest with myself, this is something I don&rsquo;t think I could&rsquo;ve accomplished in this timeframe without the assistance of AI tools like  
<a href="https://www.cursor.com/" target="_blank">Cursor</a> and  
<a href="https://chatgpt.com/" target="_blank">ChatGPT</a> (o1). In fact, if I had to guess, I would say that 90-95% of the code was AI-generated.</p>
<p>While I think tools like these are revolutionizing the software engineering field, I suspect it would&rsquo;ve taken someone without development experience quite a bit longer, mainly because the infrastructure setup and app deployment can be confusing and a bit intimidating. Getting a local Django app up and running was quite easy.</p>
<p>Cursor is one of the most impressive AI tools out there, but it&rsquo;s certainly not perfect. If you&rsquo;re not paying attention, it will add unnecessary files and duplicate existing functionality. It works best if you have a basic idea of what you&rsquo;re doing.</p>
<p>In general, as apps become more complex, these AI tools tend to require more guidance and specialized prompting.</p>
<p>Besides speed-to-market and other business metrics, this experience has me wondering whether security and reliability will be some of the key differentiators going forward.</p>
<h2 id="wrap-up">Wrap up</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! I hope you enjoy the challenges and the art!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EAGxBerkeley: Thoughts and Reflections</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 23:43:27 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For context,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I don&amp;rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&amp;rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&amp;rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&amp;rsquo;ve been to, the
&lt;a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven&lt;/a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
</p>
<p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.</p>
<p>For context,</p>
<ol>
<li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.</li>
</ol>
<p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&rsquo;ve been to, the  
<a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven</a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!</p>
<p>My goal for the conference was mostly to network and to learn from other&rsquo;s how to best organize and run a local EA group, in my case  
<a href="https://effectivealtruismla.org/" target="_blank">EA Los Angeles</a>. On both of these fronts, I would say the conference was a huge successful for me personally. Between the talks, the one-on-ones and the after-parties, I returned to my friend&rsquo;s place each evening bubbling with energy and eager to &ldquo;get to work&rdquo;!</p>
<p>To the specifics. I&rsquo;ve had a few days to organize my notes and wanted to share a few takeaways (in no particular order):</p>
<ul>
<li>While there has been impressive progress in the past couple of years, cultivated meat still appears many years away from going &ldquo;mainstream&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>I still believe supply-side interventions (real cultivated meat at a comparable price point) is the most promising path to ending or dramatically reducing factory farming.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>AI safety / security, as a field or subfield, will only continue to receive more and moreattention.ChatGPT 1o (Strawberry) was released today.
<ul>
<li>My guess is that over half of the attendees were there solely, or at least primarily, for AI safety.</li>
<li>This fields also seems to attract a lot of young, talented individuals, particularly from mathematics and computer-science backgrounds.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Much of the AI safety research is still highly theoretical.
<ul>
<li>This might be obvious (it is research after all) but part of me is eager to see a few AI safety orgs adopt a more engineering-focused approach. I think  
<a href="https://vitalik.eth.limo/general/2023/11/27/techno_optimism.html#dacc" target="_blank">Vitalik Buterin</a>&rsquo;s  
<a href="https://80000hours.org/podcast/episodes/vitalik-buterin-techno-optimism/" target="_blank">defensive acceleration</a> has a lot of merits.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In many ways, this conference felt like two simultaneous conferences, an AI-safety conference and a smaller, animal-welfare conference sharing the same venue.</li>
<li>One of my favorite talks was by Derek Shiller from Rethinking Priorities on &ldquo;Bargaining Approach to Moral Uncertainty&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>See previous bullet point about differences in priorities.</li>
<li>The topic gives <em>directionality</em>.</li>
<li>Check out  
<a href="https://parliament.rethinkpriorities.org" target="_blank">The Moral Parliament Tool</a></li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t think I have fully digested the three previous bullets&hellip;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I sat for the guided meditation on Sunday morning and was glad to see it on the schedule.
<ul>
<li>Reduce suffering through practice?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This list far from comprehensive but hopefully highlights a few of the ideas and <em>vibes</em> that I picked up at the conferences. There were a lot talks going on at the conference I wasn&rsquo;t able to attend but looking forward to catching when they are posted.</p>
<p>This conference was a wonderful showing for the community, and community is nothing more than people hanging out and enjoying each other&rsquo;s company! It&rsquo;s even more encouraging to be part of a community that is genuinely focused on making the world a better place.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What's your humor setting Co-Pilot?</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 17:00:17 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/copilot_humor_setting.jpg" alt="Meme from interstellar" width="1000">
&lt;p>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services,
&lt;a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt-plus" target="_blank">ChatGPT Plus&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" target="_blank">GitHub's Co-Pilot&lt;/a> but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &amp;ldquo;co-pilot&amp;rdquo; perfectly captures the &lt;em>current&lt;/em> relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing. As I began to type out &lt;code>url = &amp;quot;https://&lt;/code>, Co-Pilot generated a suggestion that I could accept by hitting tab. At this point, it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter what the URL was so I accepted the suggestion. Any guesses what the URL was for? What if I told you it was for a YouTube video?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/copilot_humor_setting.jpg" alt="Meme from interstellar" width="1000">
<p>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services,  
<a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt-plus" target="_blank">ChatGPT Plus</a> and  
<a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" target="_blank">GitHub's Co-Pilot</a> but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo; perfectly captures the <em>current</em> relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.</p>
<p>Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing. As I began to type out <code>url = &quot;https://</code>, Co-Pilot generated a suggestion that I could accept by hitting tab. At this point, it didn&rsquo;t matter what the URL was so I accepted the suggestion. Any guesses what the URL was for? What if I told you it was for a YouTube video?</p>
<p>If you guessed, Rick Astley&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ">&ldquo;Never Gonna Give You Up&rdquo; music video</a>, you would be correct. I got  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rickrolling" target="_blank">rickrolled</a> by my Co-Pilot, damn!</p>
<hr>
<p>Without going into too much detail on how these Large Language Models (LLMs) work, it&rsquo;s important to know that these LLMs are trained on billions and billions of lines of text data from online sources including blogs, forums, and digitized books, just to name a few.  What this means is that a large fraction of all the entertaining, beautiful, mean, hopeful, hateful, weird and wonderful things we have collectively written, have been internalized by these LLMs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not a huge surprise that a URL generated by Co-Pilot would be one of the most famous internet memes. I would guess it&rsquo;s among the top 5 common URLs found in the &ldquo;wild&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This experience has once again highlighted that interacting with these LLMs - at least at this point in their development - is like interacting with a mirror of humanity. Training these large models on our collective knowledge has proven that, when concentrated in one entity like GPT4, it has the potential to reflect the vast spectrum of human behavior and culture, both the profound and the trivial.</p>
<p>As AI continues to evolve, the line between tool and collaborator will become increasingly blurred. Today, we might see AI as a &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo;, but in the future, these systems could become more akin to partners in our creative and professional endeavors. Or perhaps AIs could dispense with the need for a human &ldquo;pilot&rdquo; altogether.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of the previous two paragraphs were completed for my by ChatGPT using the previous paragraphs as the prompt.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I will conclude by encouraging folks who create content - practically speaking, everyone - to think twice before spreading lies, hate, or any other less-than-flattering ideas that will eventually be picked up by future LLMs; we should strive to ensure the best version of humanity is captured in the future training data sets.</p>
<p>If  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning_from_human_feedback" target="_blank">reinforcement learning with human feedback</a> (RLHF) is like scolding a child who swears, then improving the training dataset is akin to not swearing in front of the child to begin with.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s not swear in front of the AI.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Giant Sequoia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:39:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson&lt;/a> on &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000"></p>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.</p>
<p>There are species of trees that thrive in this fiery environment, one such tree is the Giant Sequoia.</p>
<p>Giant Sequoias hold the record for the largest tree by volume, specifically  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/seki/learn/nature/largest-trees-in-world.htm" target="_blank">General Sherman</a> with a trunk volume of over 1,480 cubic meters (52,500 cubic feet). They can grow up to 85 meters (280 feet) tall, and their gorgeous red-brown bark can grow up to 60 centimeters (24 inches) thick. The thickness of their bark, and lack of flammable sap, make these mature Giant Sequoias resistant to most fires.</p>
<p>The reproductive process of the Giant Sequoia and forest fires are intimately linked. The cones of the Giant Sequoia are serotinous, meaning they require an external trigger — in this case, fire — to release their seeds. The heat of the raging forest fire causes these tightly sealed cones to dry out and open up, setting their seeds free. With the cleared forest floor and a fresh layer of nutrient-rich ash, these seeds have an opportunity to germinate and become the next generation of Giant Sequoias.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re up close to a mature Giant Sequoia, you can often see the scars of past fires. You might be comforted knowing their offspring may be nearby</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_fire_art.jpg" alt=" A painting of the bark of a Giant Sequoia that looks like fire." width="500"></p>
<p>As I write this, I reflect on the ideas of resilience, adaptation, and creative destruction in the broadest sense. It&rsquo;s August 2023, and some tangible form of AI is already here. Are humans like the Giant Sequoias, ready to use this power to our advantage, and to grow and develop beyond our current capabilities? Or are we like the old and dying underbrush that is about to be burnt away to make way for a new form of life?</p>
<p>Or is my analogy being stretched too far? Either way, I can&rsquo;t help but feel a sense of uncertainty about the future, a mixture of both anxiety and excitement.</p>
<p>Our ancestors harnessed the power of fire and it has been the stuff of legend ever since. It unlocked even greater opportunities for humanity and fair to say that fire has been a net positive even factoring in its destructive nature <sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence is humanity&rsquo;s newest fire! A fire that listens, speaks and creates. Some of the dangers of artificial intelligence are easy to imagine, more fake news and increased surveillance, while understanding the potential existential dangers requires a robust definition of intelligence and a basic understanding of  
<a href="https://www.alignmentforum.org/" target="_blank">the alignment problem</a>.</p>
<p>Just as the immediate dangers are easy to imagine and the truly catastrophic ones difficult to pin down, the same pattern holds for the benefits of AI. The immediate benefits of AI are here already, a personal tutorial at your fingertips and the ability to generate new content with a faction of the effort. The truly awesome changes are difficult to predict.</p>
<p>Innovations as large and sweeping as the harnessing of fire, the invention of the atomic bomb or the creation of artificial intelligence force humanity to adapt to them in fundamental ways. Will AI burn too hot and destroy the entire forest, including the mighty Giant Sequoias? Will it usher in a new era of growth and prosperity? Or will it be regulated in such a way that it&rsquo;s rendered useless?</p>
<p>Thirty years from now, we will likely know how this has played out but until then, prepare for change and try to have fun with it!</p>
<p><sup>1</sup>
One possible way that the harnessing of fire might lead to the extinction of life on Earth (a net negative) is via the nuclear bomb, the ultimate expression of fire.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>