<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Madagascar on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/tags/madagascar/</link><description>Recent content in Madagascar on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.141.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 22:15:27 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/tags/madagascar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>3 Reasons to Visit the Eighth Continent, Madagascar</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 22:15:27 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is my attempt at writing at an exciting travel blog. I found writing this to be extremely fun and hope to write more about travel in the future.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You’ve been itching to see a part of the world most people haven’t and you’re hoping to jump into some good ol’ fashion adventure. You’re not alone feeling that most places on this planet have become overrun with tourists. For better or for worse, this trend is here to stay.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is my attempt at writing at an exciting travel blog. I found writing this to be extremely fun and hope to write more about travel in the future.</em></p>
<p>You’ve been itching to see a part of the world most people haven’t and you’re hoping to jump into some good ol’ fashion adventure. You’re not alone feeling that most places on this planet have become overrun with tourists. For better or for worse, this trend is here to stay.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/fresh_coconut.jpg" alt="a freshly opened coconut in front of the beach" width="500"></p>
<p>Although adventure usually conjures up images of exotic new lands or crazy experiences, the truth is that adventure is a deeply personal quest that can be had anywhere. It just requires an open-mind and a willingness to go with the flow.</p>
<p>As travel expert and author of  
<a href="https://rolfpotts.com/books/vagabonding/" target="_blank">Vagabonding</a>, Rolf Potts puts it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“More often than not, you’ll discover that ‘adventure’ is a decision after the fact - a way of deciphering an event or an experience that you can’t quite explain.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>However that being said, let me introduce you to Madagascar, the world’s eighth continent, an island like no other place on earth. If you’ve never considered Madagascar as a travel destination before, let me outline a few reasons why you definitely should.</p>
<h2 id="1-the-adventurous-landscape">#1 The Adventurous Landscape</h2>
<p>Red earth, lush rainforests, dry desserts, beautiful beaches, terraced rice and corn fields; the landscape here is simply intoxicating.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/red_earth_ocean.jpg" alt="a river delta showing the red earth emptying into the ocean" width="500"></p>
<p>Slightly larger than mainland France, at approximately 587,000 km<sup>2</sup> (or 227,000 mi<sup>2</sup>), this island nation is both large and diverse. It also ranks as the world’s fourth largest island.</p>
<p><em>For you curious cats, the larger islands are, in decreasing order: Greenland, New Guinea and Borneo. My sources tell me Australia is considered a continent.</em></p>
<p>The rawness of the land attracts anyone who loves outdoor adventure; you can hike, swim, snorkel or scuba dive, cycle, or simply sit and observe the country’s unique beauty. And, like most places, these activities are either free or very cheap. The exception being scuba diving.</p>
<p>Just pick an adventure.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/boat_at_sunset.jpg" alt="a single boat with the sun setting in the background" width="500"></p>
<p>Ride a rented bike up a hill for a view of the surrounding landscape while being greeted by locals along the way. “Salama!”</p>
<p>Snorkel or scuba dive off the southwest coast to catch a glimpse of one of the world’s largest barrier reefs (well, before it gets completely destroyed).</p>
<p><em>I splurged and got  
<a href="https://www.atimoo.com/en/" target="_blank">PADI certified</a> which consisted of 7 dives over 5 days. 5 out of 5 starfish, would do again.</em></p>
<p>Stroll through the city markets of Antsirabe taking in the sites and sounds of a bustling city while  munching on fresh baguette and drinking a cup of coffee that costs a combined 0.25USD.</p>
<p>Or if you’re lucky, watch enormous lightning bolts crack over nearby hills while above you the cloudless night sky reveals the Milky Way.</p>
<p>Whatever you do, definitely explore some of the amazing national parks. Visit Isalo National Park, dubbed The Grand Canyon of Madagascar by my park guide or chase cute Golden Bamboo lemurs through the rainforest in the Ranomafana National Park.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/valley_sky.jpg" alt="a view of the canyon known as the Grand Canyon of Madagascar" width="500"></p>
<p>This list wouldn’t be complete if it didn’t include sites such as the famous Avenue of the Baobabs, picturesque Nosy Be, or the two Tsingy National Park known for their jagged rocks formations and incredible endemic biodiversity.</p>
<p>Although getting around the island can be difficult - this goes for hired drivers or taking the taxi-brousse - don’t forget to enjoy the landscape as you drive through the country; you’re destination will undoubtedly reward you for your patience.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/taxi_brousse.jpg" alt="a taxi-brousse (bush taxi) being loaded for an upcoming trip" width="500"></p>
<h2 id="2-the-flora-and-fauna">#2 The Flora and Fauna</h2>
<p>Reason number two for visiting Madagascar is the incredible biodiversity; 90% of all plants and 70% of all animals are endemic to the island (found nowhere else in the world).</p>
<p>For instance, of the nine baobab tree species, six of them are only found in Madagascar, including the giant baobab.</p>
<p>Madagascar is also home of the lemur, more like over a hundred species of lemur. These monkey-like mammals are found in most of their National Parks and come in many varieties.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/baobab.jpg" alt="a unknown species of baobab" width="500"></p>
<p>There are twelve species of lemur in Ranomafana National Park alone, include the endemic small Golden Bamboo lemur (a matriarchal species). Or if you visit Isalo National Park, you can spot the famous ring-tailed lemur scaling cliffs with easy or simply hanging around the picnic area.</p>
<p><em>As a reminder, don’t feed wild animals. Though none of my park guides did, I have heard that some might in order to impress tourists.</em></p>
<p>Sadly, many lemur species and much of the biodiversity on the island is being threatened by deforestation and general human activity. Though the government is taking some action, many fear it’s not enough.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/lemurs.jpg" alt="two ring-tailed lemurs" width="500"></p>
<p>Often overlooked by tourists are the wonderful array of birds, reptiles, amphibians, flowers, and insects. And unlike Australia, most of the wildlife here isn’t out to kill you.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/chameleon.jpg" alt="a chameleon on the trunk of a small tree" width="500"></p>
<p><em>But who the hell wants to see insects?</em></p>
<p>One insect hard to miss is the non-venomous Golden Orb-Weaver spider. It’s truly a sight to behold, though perhaps from a distance. These nearly palm-sized spiders are found throughout the island and make you appreciate our elevated status in the food-web.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/spider_snaking.jpg" alt="a large spider ready to consume a recently trapped moth" width="500"></p>
<p>Animal-lover, tree-hugger, or not, Madagascar’s flora and fauna might not appear all the different at first glance, however upon closer examination,
you will find an alien world like nowhere else in the world.</p>
<h2 id="3-the-people">#3 The People</h2>
<p>Though a bit cliché, the most memorable experiences as a traveler often come from your interactions with new people, locals and other travelers alike.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/street_view.jpg" alt="a view of the street as people go about their daily business" width="500"></p>
<p>The Malagasy people - people from Madagascar - tend to be reserved but are generally very friendly. Be it with the person sitting next you on the bus, the receptionists at your hotel, or your National Park guide, you will be rewarded with more intimate knowledge of the country and the people if you can start a conversation.</p>
<p><em>Like most countries I have visited, rich or poor, the population is as interested in your country or culture as you might be in theirs. Ask respectful questions, answer theirs and make a friend in the process.</em></p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/mountain_house.jpg" alt="a small house with a steep, forested-mountain behind it" width="500"></p>
<p>One such example is that of Daha, a National Park guide in Ranomafana National Park, someone who cares greatly about the forest and animals. However, what made the interaction with him so much more engaging was the fact that he was just as curious about United States and Europe as I was in Madagascar.</p>
<p>Nicolas is another example of a local who, through sharing his experiences, added texture and context to the visit. He is a math student at the local university working at the Madagascar Underground hostel. He shared stories about the different tribes on the island and eventually through conversation explained how he took the initiative to coach soccer to the deaf students at his university.</p>
<p>What a badass!</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/lake_anosy.jpg" alt="a view of Lake Anosy from Haute Ville" width="500"></p>
<p>Then there are the other travelers you will meet.</p>
<p>Relative to its size, Madagascar receives very few tourists; fewer than 300,000 visited the island in 2016.</p>
<p>Although not a prime backpackers destination, those who do travel here, the Madagascar Underground hostel is a great place to begin your adventure.</p>
<p><em>I was told this is the only hostel on the island.</em></p>
<p>I meet a generous and entertaining Chinese man, who has been on the road for the past two years, at Madagascar Underground. We left the hostel together and ended up spending a week traveling together.</p>
<p>I was also lucky enough to spend time traveling with a Belgian woman who had been on the island volunteering for five months.  </p>
<p>And the last week I was on there, I befriended a Spanish woman who was leaving the island after spending the previous two years working as a dive instructor.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/bedroom_hut.jpg" alt="a small hut for sleeping and a view of the green valley behind it" width="500"></p>
<p>Interactions like these, along with many others, are the reason why traveling can be so much fun and exciting. And although you can meet interesting people and have such experiences anywhere on the planet, Madagascar felt different because of its remoteness and unique beauty.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>