<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Posts on eskild.blog</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.141.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.eskild.blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>eskild.art: building for the future</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 22:31:33 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2025-01-05-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on
&lt;a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&amp;rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django&lt;/a> with
&lt;a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS&lt;/a> using Postgres deployed on Google&amp;rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Art and AI but not AI-generated art.</em></p>
<h2 id="updated-tech-stack">Updated Tech Stack</h2>
<p>During this recent holiday break, I had some time to work on  
<a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art</a>, and I&rsquo;m excited to share those updates here. Although I haven&rsquo;t added any new art (yet), the site has been redesigned from the ground up.</p>
<p>The initial version was a FastAPI app on GCP Cloud Run using basic HTML Jinja templates; it was simple but got the job done. The new version is now running  
<a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank">Django</a> with  
<a href="https://django-tailwind.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html" target="_blank">Tailwind CSS</a> using Postgres deployed on Google&rsquo;s Kubernetes Engine (GKE).</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://x.com/dexhorthy/status/856639005462417409" target="_blank">It&rsquo;s certainly amusing</a> to see a basic web app deployed on a compute environment which is orders of magnitude more expensive than the previous environment. However, I wanted to take this opportunity to brush up on Kubernetes and GCP while leaving room to growth. Who knows, maybe one day I&rsquo;ll deploying it on the Kubernetes cluster running on my  
<a href="https://eskild.blog/posts/2024-08-27-hl0/" target="_blank">homelab</a> ;)</p>
<p>I chose Django because it has many great features &ldquo;out-of-the-box,&rdquo; such as the admin panel and because I resonate with their slogan: &ldquo;The web framework for perfectionists with deadlines.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="coding-with-ai">Coding with AI</h2>
<p>Going from an empty repo to a simple site deployed on GKE in less than three weeks is moderately impressive. That said, considering this was something I hacked on a few hours here and there, I quite pleased.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m being honest with myself, this is something I don&rsquo;t think I could&rsquo;ve accomplished in this timeframe without the assistance of AI tools like  
<a href="https://www.cursor.com/" target="_blank">Cursor</a> and  
<a href="https://chatgpt.com/" target="_blank">ChatGPT</a> (o1). In fact, if I had to guess, I would say that about 90% of the code was AI-generated.</p>
<p>While I think tools like these are revolutionizing the software engineering field, I suspect it would&rsquo;ve taken someone without development experience quite a bit longer, mainly because the infrastructure setup and app deployment can be confusing and a bit intimidating. Getting a local Django app up and running was the easy part.</p>
<p>Cursor is one of the most impressive AI tools out there, but it&rsquo;s certainly not perfect. If you&rsquo;re not paying attention, it will add unnecessary files and duplicate existing functionality; hallucinations (or rather confabulations) are problems I don&rsquo;t see getting fully resolved anytime soon.</p>
<p>In general, these tools works best if you have a basic idea of what you&rsquo;re doing. And as the codebase become more complex, these AI tools tend to require more guidance and specialized prompting.</p>
<p>Besides speed-to-market and other business metrics, this experience has me wondering whether security and reliability will be some of the key differentiators going forward. We will likely see a lot more apps deployed by non-developers in the coming years but I suspect once their app start gaining traction, professional developers will come in and ensure the site can scale, is reliable and adheres to security best practices.</p>
<h2 id="wrap-up">Wrap up</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! I hope you enjoy the challenges and the art!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Return to Norway</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-30-norway/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 12:38:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-30-norway/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/norwegian_coast.jpg" alt="View of Oslofjord, on the Norwegian coast" width="1000">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last weekend was the first time in over 16 years that I returned to Norway, my birthplace and the home of my father&amp;rsquo;s side of the family. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any good reason for not returning sooner, and even fewer good reasons since graduating from university.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I prepared for the visit and reached out to family and old friends, I felt this internal resistance and sense of fear. But what was there to be scared of?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/norwegian_coast.jpg" alt="View of Oslofjord, on the Norwegian coast" width="1000">
</p>
<p>Last weekend was the first time in over 16 years that I returned to Norway, my birthplace and the home of my father&rsquo;s side of the family. I don&rsquo;t have any good reason for not returning sooner, and even fewer good reasons since graduating from university.</p>
<p>As I prepared for the visit and reached out to family and old friends, I felt this internal resistance and sense of fear. But what was there to be scared of?</p>
<p>It took talking it out with a few friends and writing this post before I recognized that it was partially, if not mostly, centered around personal identity.</p>
<p>What one identifies with is quite personal but generally not all that mysterious. Most of us identify with the culture in which we were raised. This includes preferring the culture&rsquo;s food, speaking the shared language, celebrating the culture&rsquo;s important holidays—shallow cultural markers—and embracing and investing in the culture&rsquo;s religion and core values—deep cultural markers.</p>
<p>As much as I enjoy Norwegian food, as a vegan<sup>1</sup>, I can&rsquo;t consume the vast majority of it. And although Norwegian was my first language, after the age of thirteen, I hardly ever spoke it again and my ability to speak it has since atrophied to an embarrassing degree.</p>
<p>When I returned to Norway, my implicit rejection of the shallow cultural values made it obvious to me, and surely to my family and friends, that I was not as &ldquo;Norwegian&rdquo; as my passport or my name might suggest. Or as &ldquo;Norwegian&rdquo; as I used to be.</p>
<p>I was scared that I would be rejected or made to feel like an outsider. Whether this was a legitimate fear or not is beside the point; speaking to one&rsquo;s family in English instead of our native Norwegian is (and was) a little uncomfortable.</p>
<p>Ultimately, none of these fears came to pass, and I was welcomed home with open arms!</p>
<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve had a few days to let the experience sink in, what did I learn, where does this leave me?</p>
<p>First, learn from my mistake, and don&rsquo;t let fear or discomfort stop you from rekindling old relationships<sup>2</sup>. I had plans to visit my sick grandma in Norway in 2015, but by the time I finished my university quarter, it was too late, and she had passed away. I never had a chance to say goodbye.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t want any more such experiences. Sit with the discomfort of being reacquainted for but a moment, it&rsquo;s worth it.</p>
<p>Second, Paul Graham wrote an essay in 2009 titled  
<a href="https://www.paulgraham.com/identity.html" target="_blank">&ldquo;Keep your identity small&rdquo;</a>, and I think about this essay quite often. For me, keeping my identity small means avoiding the trap of reflexively defending bad ideas or harmful practices because I identify with the group or individuals who promote them.</p>
<p>Norway—like all other countries and cultures—has many wonderful features, but I strive to evaluate each one as impartially as I can. Admittedly, this is a lot easier said than done, but it is also worth it.</p>
<p>And third, shallow cultural markers are usually a lot more visible and therefore get more attention. Deep cultural markers on the other hand, are much more difficult to explicitly express, at least not without some expensive commitment.</p>
<p>Have I made any commitments that are an expression of some deeper values? Shouldn&rsquo;t I? And in which direction?</p>
<p>These are questions I&rsquo;m wresting with but I believe the answer lies somewhere between having the courage to be an individual while remembering that deep integration with family, friends, and the natural world, is where the magic truly lies.</p>
<hr>
<p><sup>1</sup> I care for the animals but reject &ldquo;vegan&rdquo; as an identity, for reasons outlined below.</p>
<p><sup>2</sup> Not all relationships are worth rekindling, but I would guess many more are than are not.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EAGxBerkeley: Thoughts and Reflections</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 23:43:27 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-09-12-eagxb24/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For context,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I don&amp;rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&amp;rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&amp;rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&amp;rsquo;ve been to, the
&lt;a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven&lt;/a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/eagxberkeley.jpg" alt="EAGxBerkeley Logo with conference dates" width="400">
</p>
<p>I attended EAGxBerkeley last weekend, and wanted to capture a few thoughts and ideas before my memory taints them any further.</p>
<p>For context,</p>
<ol>
<li>this was my first EA conference, making it hard for me to compare with other EA conferences,</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t live in the Bay Area so part of my excitement might be an artifact of the novelty and being with friends, and,</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a software engineer who uses and builds with AI on a regular basis but I&rsquo;m not an AI safety researcher.</li>
</ol>
<p>At a high-level, I would rate this among the most entertaining and worthwhile conferences I&rsquo;ve attended; it was also hosted at one of the most unique venues I&rsquo;ve been to, the  
<a href="https://www.lighthaven.space/" target="_blank">Lighthaven</a>. The event organizers and volunteers deserve another round of applause for all of their great work!</p>
<p>My goal for the conference was mostly to network and to learn from other&rsquo;s how to best organize and run a local EA group, in my case  
<a href="https://effectivealtruismla.org/" target="_blank">EA Los Angeles</a>. On both of these fronts, I would say the conference was a huge success. Between the talks, the one-on-ones and the after-parties, I returned to my friend&rsquo;s place each evening bubbling with energy and eager to &ldquo;get to work&rdquo;!</p>
<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve had a few days to organize my notes and wanted to share a few takeaways (in no particular order):</p>
<ul>
<li>While there has been impressive progress in the past couple of years, cultivated meat still appears many years away from going &ldquo;mainstream&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>I still believe supply-side interventions (real cultivated meat at a comparable price point) is the most promising path to ending or dramatically reducing factory farming.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>AI safety / security, as a field or subfield, will only continue to receive more and more attention. ChatGPT o1 was released today for some additional context.
<ul>
<li>My guess is that over half of the attendees were there solely, or at least primarily, for AI safety.</li>
<li>This fields also seems to attract a lot of young, talented individuals, particularly from mathematics and computer-science backgrounds.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Much of the AI safety research is still highly theoretical.
<ul>
<li>This might be obvious (it is research after all) but part of me is eager to see a few AI safety orgs adopt a more engineering-focused approach. I think  
<a href="https://vitalik.eth.limo/general/2023/11/27/techno_optimism.html#dacc" target="_blank">Vitalik Buterin</a>&rsquo;s  
<a href="https://80000hours.org/podcast/episodes/vitalik-buterin-techno-optimism/" target="_blank">defensive acceleration</a> has a lot of merits.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In many ways, this conference felt like two simultaneous conferences, an AI-safety conference and a smaller, animal-welfare conference sharing the same venue.</li>
<li>One of my favorite talks was by Derek Shiller from Rethinking Priorities on &ldquo;Bargaining Approach to Moral Uncertainty&rdquo;.
<ul>
<li>See previous bullet point about differences in priorities.</li>
<li>The topic gives <em>directionality</em>.</li>
<li>Check out  
<a href="https://parliament.rethinkpriorities.org" target="_blank">The Moral Parliament Tool</a></li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t think I have fully digested the three previous bullets&hellip;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I sat for the guided meditation on Sunday morning and was glad to see it on the schedule.
<ul>
<li>Reduce suffering through practice?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This list far from comprehensive but hopefully highlights a few of the ideas and <em>vibes</em> that I picked up at the conferences. There were many talks I was unfortunately unable to attend but I look forward to catching when they are posted on YouTube.</p>
<p>This conference was a wonderful showing for the community, and community is nothing more than people hanging out and enjoying each other&rsquo;s company! It&rsquo;s even more encouraging to be part of a community that is genuinely focused on making the world a better place.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>In the beginning, there was hardware</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-08-27-hl0/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 22:15:22 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-08-27-hl0/</guid><description>&lt;p>The home lab. Sounds cool, you should get yourself one ;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s how I got started quickly and cheaply.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="requirements">Requirements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Besides cost and speed, I have a few other requirements and preferences that should help simplify the process and hopefully make it more useful long-term.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, given that I&amp;rsquo;m writing this on my M1 Macbook - with it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code>arm&lt;/code> chip - it makes sense for me to have a dedicated &lt;code>x86_64&lt;/code> machine. Second, I want a stable, widely used, Linux OS meant for servers. One that has a package manager with large selection of packages but also plenty of resources online to help me troubleshoot and learn.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The home lab. Sounds cool, you should get yourself one ;)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s how I got started quickly and cheaply.</p>
<h2 id="requirements">Requirements</h2>
<p>Besides cost and speed, I have a few other requirements and preferences that should help simplify the process and hopefully make it more useful long-term.</p>
<p>First, given that I&rsquo;m writing this on my M1 Macbook - with it&rsquo;s <code>arm</code> chip - it makes sense for me to have a dedicated <code>x86_64</code> machine. Second, I want a stable, widely used, Linux OS meant for servers. One that has a package manager with large selection of packages but also plenty of resources online to help me troubleshoot and learn.</p>
<p>The answer, Ubuntu Server. Shocker!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Basically whenever I have to make a decision between a few options, the rule-of-thumb is to go with the simple, common solution.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Next, I need to decide what software to run on this home lab. For me, the immediate choice is Kubernetes. I want to learn more about how to manage a Kubernetes cluster without relying on one of the cloud providers to do it for me and this would be a fun opportunity to do so.</p>
<p>At first, this &ldquo;cluster&rdquo; will consist of one node which means application-specific pods will run on the same node as the control-plane and api server. Definitely not recommended for any serious workload but not a big deal as I get started.</p>
<p>Some might be asking why not just run multiple nodes on a VM layer. I may still do that but the idea of setting up a Kubernetes cluster on &ldquo;bare-metal&rdquo; sounds kind of cooool. Add a few more CPU nodes and perhaps a few GPUs and the possibility of running AI workloads is just that much closer.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m getting a little ahead of myself.</p>
<h2 id="hardware">Hardware</h2>
<p>Now to the hardware.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Where I can and if the price is right, I&rsquo;ll go with used/refurbished.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here at the core components that I ended up purchasing:</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08MMQH98H?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" target="_blank">Lenovo ThinkCentre M910Q - refurbished</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Intel Core i7-6700T</li>
<li>32GB RAM</li>
<li>1TB NVMe SSD</li>
<li>Price: $250</li>
</ul>
<p>It came in great condition and with a keyboard and mouse. A bangin&rsquo; deal if you ask me!</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0778Y6K6N?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" target="_blank">Netgear Powerline Adapter Kit - used</a></p>
<ul>
<li>2 Gigabit Ethernet Ports with Passthrough</li>
<li>Price $56</li>
</ul>
<p>This was necessary for me and may not be for you. The modem and router in my apartment are in my roommate&rsquo;s room. So to get ethernet to the home lab, I was able to use these adapters which transmit the ethernet signal over the cooper power cables in the house. This is a cleaner solution than running a long cable through the house.</p>
<p> 
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00K4DS5KU?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" target="_blank">TP-Link 8 Port Switch - new, half-off</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Price: $27</li>
</ul>
<p>Not entirely necessary at this stage but will makes it easy to add additional machines in the future.</p>
<p>That brings the price of hardware to <strong>$333 + taxes/shipping</strong>. Nice!</p>
<p>In the process, I will make a few changes to my home office including reorganzing the office closet. Here are a few additional purchases I made to help organize my things a little better:</p>
<ul>
<li> 
<a href="https://www.homedepot.com/p/HDX-4-Tier-Steel-Wire-Shelving-Unit-in-Chrome-36-in-W-x-54-in-H-x-14-in-D-31436PS-1/203846480" target="_blank">A new steel-wire shelving unit - Home Depot</a></li>
<li> 
<a href="https://www.homedepot.com/p/NTW-15-ft-Cat6-Snagless-Shielded-STP-Network-Patch-Cable-Yellow-345-S6-015YL/300457291" target="_blank">15ft cat6 cable - Home Depot</a></li>
<li> 
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07MH6DGMM?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details" target="_blank">Cable tie mounts - Amazon</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Luckily I had an old monitor lying around I used for the initially server setup. Finally with a pair of scissors, a few zip ties and a power strip, I have all that I need to get started.</p>
<h3 id="hardware-setup">Hardware Setup</h3>
<p>The setup is straight forward.</p>
<p>Plug in one Powerline Adapter to outlet near the router and then connect it to the router with an ethernet cable.</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/homelab/powerline_adapter.jpg" alt="Powerline Adapter plugged into the outlet directly" width="250">
</p>
<p>Plug in the other Powerline Adapter near the home lab and connect it to the switch (yellow cable). Connect the switch to the home lab (black cable).</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/homelab/hl_setup_0.jpg" alt="" width="650">
</p>
<p>Connect the monitor, keyboard and mouse, then turn on the server.</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/homelab/hl_keyboard.jpg" alt="" width="400">
</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s it for the hardware setup.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m excited to get started with this project. I&rsquo;ve been wanting to do this for a while and I&rsquo;m glad I&rsquo;m finally getting around to it. In another post, I&rsquo;ll go over the the initial configuration of the server and Kubernetes setup.</p>
<p><em>Looks over both shoulders</em>&hellip;. I just setup a desktop computer in my office closet and called it a home server.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Jumping off cliffs</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-06-02-cliffs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 01:00:36 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2024-06-02-cliffs/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/grand_canyon.jpg" alt="Grand Canyon (1924) by Gunnar Mauritz Widforss" width="1000">
&lt;a href="https://artvee.com/dl/grand-canyon#00">Grand Canyon (1924) by Gunnar Mauritz Widforss&lt;/a>
&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We have to continually be jumping off cliffs and developing our wings on the way down.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This quote by
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_Vonnegut" target="_blank">Kurt Vonnegut&lt;/a> has been on my mind since I encountered it about a month ago. Good quotes can capture a truth about the world in an elegant and poetic ways, always making you wish you had come up with it yourself. The difficulty in trying to describe certain truths is that they cannot, by their very nature, be expressed in language.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/grand_canyon.jpg" alt="Grand Canyon (1924) by Gunnar Mauritz Widforss" width="1000">
<a href="https://artvee.com/dl/grand-canyon#00">Grand Canyon (1924) by Gunnar Mauritz Widforss</a>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We have to continually be jumping off cliffs and developing our wings on the way down.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This quote by  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_Vonnegut" target="_blank">Kurt Vonnegut</a> has been on my mind since I encountered it about a month ago. Good quotes can capture a truth about the world in an elegant and poetic ways, always making you wish you had come up with it yourself. The difficulty in trying to describe certain truths is that they cannot, by their very nature, be expressed in language.</p>
<p>So what truth does this quote gesture at? Why must we continually jump? And how does one develop wings?</p>
<p>In my own way of gesturing at these underlying ideas, I will reflect on a few other quotes.</p>
<p>From <em> 
<a href="https://dynamic.wakingup.com/course/C96FE0?code=SC2F01AF8&amp;share_id=0933DE54&amp;source=content%20share" target="_blank">Destiny</a></em><sup>1</sup>, a poem by  
<a href="https://davidwhyte.com/" target="_blank">David Whyte</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Strangely, every person always lives out their destiny no matter what they do, according to the way they shape the conversation&hellip; [our destiny&rsquo;s] promise may depend upon a brave participation, a willingness to hazard ourselves in a difficult world, a certain form of wild generosity with our gifts;&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Our experience of life &ldquo;may depend upon a brave participation&rdquo; — the courage to admit ignorance while striving to eliminate it, the courage to say &ldquo;I love you&rdquo; even if you&rsquo;re unsure you&rsquo;ll hear it repeated back to you, and the courage to look like a fool while you&rsquo;re improving your trade.</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/the_gust.jpg" alt="A Ship on the High Seas Caught by a Squall, Known as ‘The Gust’ (c. 1680) " height="650">
<a href="https://artvee.com/dl/a-ship-on-the-high-seas-caught-by-a-squall-known-as-the-gust/">The Gust (c. 1680) by Willem van de Velde the Younger</a>
</p>
<p>From  
<a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/" target="_blank">Michael Nielsen</a> on <em> 
<a href="https://conversationswithtyler.com/episodes/michael-nielsen/" target="_blank">Conversations with Tyler</a></em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You&rsquo;re constantly expanding the legible, and when you do that, there&rsquo;s this penumbra of illegibility that surrounds it. That moves, but it gives you access to those other spaces.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To think &ldquo;I&rsquo;m done, that&rsquo;s it&rdquo; is a terrible mistake; we must always be vigilant and ready to learn. As the &ldquo;other spaces&rdquo; around you expand, you must face them with renewed bravery and a deeper appreciation of what came before.</p>
<p>From  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne_Gretzky" target="_blank">Wayne Gretzky</a>, NHL hockey player (and me after my missed jump shot):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You miss 100% of the shots you don&rsquo;t take.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You develop into a shooter by taking shots. There is no other way. This understanding unlocks a certain freedom; to grow, one needs to be challenged, and ultimately, it&rsquo;s not personal.</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/laundress.jpg" alt="The Laundress (1863) by Honoré Daumier" height="650">
<a href="https://artvee.com/dl/the-laundress-6/#00">The Laundress (1863) by Honoré Daumier</a>
</p>
<p>And why must we <em>continually</em> jump off cliffs? Isn&rsquo;t once enough?</p>
<p>From  
<a href="https://www.mercatus.org/scholars/dean-ball" target="_blank">Dean W. Ball</a> on <em> 
<a href="https://www.hyperdimensional.co/p/on-ai-alignment-and-superalignment" target="_blank">Hyperdimensional</a></em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not know the answer, and it doubtful that there is such a thing as &ldquo;an answer&rdquo; to problems of this kind [AI safety]. It is not just that finding the answer will be a process. The answer <em>will be</em> the process.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Essential processes that don&rsquo;t evolve to survive in the new environment die. Adaptability is, has, and will likely always be an important ingredient for success. To be good at adaptation, you need to continually adapt.</p>
<p>And from  
<a href="https://www.mayaangelou.com/" target="_blank">Maya Angelo</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Courage is the most important of all the virtues because without courage, you can&rsquo;t practice any other virtue consistently.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doing something once doesn&rsquo;t require the same courage as doing it consistently does. We must continually admit ignorance, say &ldquo;I love you,&rdquo; and feel like fools because doing so continually is the only way to improve and find new cliffs to jump off of.</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/yosemite_valley.jpg" alt="Looking Down Yosemite Valley (1865) by Albert Bierstadt" width="650">
<a href="https://artvee.com/dl/looking-down-yosemite-valley-california#00">Looking Down Yosemite Valley (1865) by Albert Bierstadt</a>
</p>
<hr>
<p><sup>1</sup> Or a  
<a href="https://www.facebook.com/PoetDavidWhyte/posts/destinyalways-has-a-possessor-as-in-my-destiny-or-your-destiny-or-her-destiny-it/1802668076425854/?paipv=0&amp;eav=AfbJoXMWgUxf9y1woxqM0Doi5KXIuBke4W0wvmE50aZBv05optV92rDZgr2M6vQfHh0&amp;_rdr" target="_blank">link to the poem on Facebook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Smartphones as Pocketknives</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-05-pk/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 08:38:54 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-05-pk/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/smartphone_pocketknife.jpg" alt="A smartphone with tools coming out." width="1000">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Modern smartphones retain the name of the tool they were initially designed as, phones. The irony is that making traditional phone calls probably makes up only a tiny fraction of what most people use their phones for these days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you’re an iPhone user, have a look at your
&lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/108806" target="_blank">Screen Time&lt;/a> to get a more accurate sense of how you &lt;em>actually&lt;/em> use your phone. If I had to guess, social media, video streaming, and messaging top the list, and perhaps in quantities that you would be a little embarrassed to admit.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center">
<img src="/images/smartphone_pocketknife.jpg" alt="A smartphone with tools coming out." width="1000">
</p>
<p>Modern smartphones retain the name of the tool they were initially designed as, phones. The irony is that making traditional phone calls probably makes up only a tiny fraction of what most people use their phones for these days.</p>
<p>If you’re an iPhone user, have a look at your  
<a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/108806" target="_blank">Screen Time</a> to get a more accurate sense of how you <em>actually</em> use your phone. If I had to guess, social media, video streaming, and messaging top the list, and perhaps in quantities that you would be a little embarrassed to admit.</p>
<p>This post aims to convince you that we should reframe our relationship to our smartphones, and in the process, become a lot more selective about what we allow on them. The framing I would like us to consider is captured by the title of the post, <em>Smartphones as Pocketknives</em>; a device with several distinct tools that is used as needed and returned to our pockets when not.</p>
<p>In the coming sections, I will share a few tips and techniques that I’ve discovered or developed over the years that have fundamentally altered how and when I use my smartphone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This post focuses on techniques specific to Apple iPhones. I also assume you have another device such as a tablet, laptop, or desktop.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="why-make-this-change">Why make this change?</h2>
<p>You make the changes I outline below because you have this nagging sense that one of the most important pieces of technology in your life is not serving you.</p>
<p>You make these changes because after 3 hours of scrolling Reddit or watching YouTube video after YouTube video, you feel guilty and somehow kind of dirty.</p>
<p>You make these changes because you recognize you don’t want to be the couple at a fancy restaurant fiddling away on your phone instead of sharing a romantic meal.</p>
<p>You make these changes because you’re tired of magically finding yourself on your phone unable to remember when you stopped working and started goofing off.</p>
<p>It wasn’t always this way.</p>
<p>Reframing our relationship with our phones and drastically reducing how much time we spend on them won’t solve all of your problems but it might, all things being equal, slowly help you improve your attention span.</p>
<p>We’ve all heard of a friend or some celebrity ditching their smartphone - sometimes for a “dumb” flip phone or sometimes for no phone at all - and we’ve half-jokingly longed for the same escape. The changes I’m proposing try to thread the needle between two extremes - the doom-scrolling NPC and the technology-bashing luddite - and hopefully empower us to use this incredible technology a bit more wisely.</p>
<h2 id="purge-purge-and-purge-some-more">Purge, purge, and purge some more</h2>
<p>My first recommendation is simple, purge any application that falls into one of the following categories:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>social media</strong>: Facebook, Instagram, Tik-Tok, Snapchat, X (Twitter), Reddit, etc.</li>
<li><strong>news &amp; sports</strong>: CNN, New York Times, Fox News, ESPN, NBA, NFL, etc.</li>
<li><strong>video streaming</strong>: YouTube, Netflix, Prime Video, Hulu, etc.</li>
<li><strong>gaming &amp; dating</strong>: You know the ones&hellip;</li>
<li><strong>third-party browsers</strong>: Chrome, Firefox, etc. (more on why this is important later)</li>
<li><strong>shopping</strong>: Amazon, Walmart, Etsy, etc.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>HARD MODE: Stop following the news all together.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">
<img src="/images/purge_apps.jpg" alt="Personified apps running away from an axe murderer" width="500">
</p>
<p>That might be more than half of the apps on your phone but I think it’s important to purge any app that pulls on your attention in unhelpful ways. Personally, the list above is ranked in descending order of how distracting (and harmful) they have the potential to be.</p>
<p>I can already hear some of you saying, I need <em>[insert app]</em> for my job. My first question is, do you really? And if that’s truly the case, can the job function not be performed on another device such as your laptop? Can you request a work phone from your company? And if none of those are feasible, would you consider setting a firm  
<a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/set-up-screen-time-for-yourself-iphb0c7313c9/ios" target="_blank">App Limit</a>, say 1 hour a day?</p>
<p>Of course, some apps can’t realistically be used on any other device other than your smartphone, specifically Snapchat and Instagram (at least for posting new content). For those apps, honestly consider how important they are to you, and if you still want them on your phone, try subjecting them to strict App Limits.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>HARD MODE: Delete or deactivate all of your social media.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can, of course, add an App Limit to any of the apps that I recommended removing but where&rsquo;s the challenge in that?</p>
<h2 id="lock-it-down">Lock it down</h2>
<p>At this point, your phone may be unrecognizable to you. But we can go further.</p>
<p>If you took my advice above and removed all third-party browsers, we can use a few additional iPhone Screen Time features to lock down your phone even further.</p>
<p>It’s no good removing the YouTube app, only to navigate to youtube.com in your phone’s browser. Therefore my recommendation is to block all of the sites whose apps you just removed - all social media sites, streaming sites, news and sports sites, etc.</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 1: Navigate to <strong>Settings</strong>
    <img src="/images/iphone_settings_icon.jpg" alt="The iPhone settings icon." width="150">
</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 2: <strong>Screen Time</strong>
    <img src="/images/iphone_settings.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone settings menu." width="300">
</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 3: <strong>Content & Privacy Restrictions</strong>
    <img src="/images/iphone_screen_time.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone screen time menu." width="300">
</p>
<p>For these changes to take effect, you will need to toggle the <code>Content &amp; Privacy Restrictions</code> button.</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 4: <strong>Content Restrictions</strong>
    <img src="/images/iphone_content_restrictions.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone privacy and content restriction menu." width="300">
</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 5: <strong>Web Content</strong>
    <img src="/images/iphone_web_content.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone content restriction menu." width="300">        
</p>
<p>It may also be worth setting the allowed web content to “Limit Adult Websites” as well, especially for you young (and not so young) lads out there.</p>
<p align="center">
    Step 6: Add sites to the <strong>Never Allow</strong> list
    <img src="/images/iphone_web_content_never_allow.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone web content menu." width="300">
</p>
<p>Finally, I highly recommend setting a  
<a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/108806" target="_blank">Screen Time Passcode</a> so that you are forced to acknowledge when you are breaking your own rules - this will also apply to App Limits.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>HARD MODE: Have a friend or partner set the Screen Time Passcode for you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <img src="/images/iphone_screen_time_passcode.jpg" alt="Screenshot of iPhone web content menu." width="300">
</p>
<p>If you’ve gotten this far, pause and congratulate yourself! In the coming days and weeks, the urge to distract yourself with your phone will hopefully decrease, and with it, the “attention muscles” should start to strengthen.</p>
<p>Now, what tools do you want in your pocketknife?</p>
<h2 id="make-it-your-own">Make it your own</h2>
<p>I think of my smartphone as a device for primarily a handful of activities, these include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>communication</strong>: Phone, Messages,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/whatsapp-messenger/id310633997" target="_blank">WhatsApp</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/signal-private-messenger/id874139669" target="_blank">Signal</a>, etc.</li>
<li><strong>health &amp; fitness</strong>:  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/streaks/id963034692" target="_blank">Streaks</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/nike-run-club-running-coach/id387771637" target="_blank">Nike Run Club</a>, Health, etc.</li>
<li><strong>productivity</strong>: Calendar,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/lr/app/todoist-to-do-list-planner/id572688855" target="_blank">Todoist</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/chatgpt/id6448311069" target="_blank">ChatGPT</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/microsoft-onedrive/id477537958" target="_blank">OneDrive</a>, Reminders, etc.</li>
<li><strong>finance</strong>:  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ynab/id1010865877" target="_blank">YNAB</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/venmo/id351727428" target="_blank">Venmo</a>, banking apps, etc.</li>
<li><strong>entertainment</strong>:  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/spotify-music-and-podcasts/id324684580" target="_blank">Spotify</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/waking-up-meditation-wisdom/id1307736395" target="_blank">Waking Up</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/overcast/id888422857" target="_blank">Overcast</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/matter-read-listen-learn/id1501592184" target="_blank">Matter</a>, etc.</li>
<li><strong>travel</strong>: Maps,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/flighty-live-flight-tracker/id1358823008" target="_blank">Flighty</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/uber-request-a-ride/id368677368" target="_blank">Uber</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/airalo-esim-travel-internet/id1475911720" target="_blank">Airalo</a>,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/google-translate/id414706506" target="_blank">Google Translate</a>, airline apps, etc.</li>
<li><strong>utilities</strong>: Camera, Calculator,  
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/microsoft-authenticator/id983156458" target="_blank">2FA authenticator</a>, insurance and home utility apps, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>Each app has a specific purpose and none of them require any real willpower to stay off of — one of the keys to avoiding prolonged time on your phone.</p>
<p>To reduce the number of times your phone interrupts you, also try limiting push notifications to only apps that require your immediate attention, more on  
<a href="#focus-modes">Focus Mode</a> below.</p>
<h2 id="make-it-beautiful">Make it beautiful</h2>
<p>When the iPhone was first introduced in 2007, the home screen could only be black, there were no widgets, no Focus modes, no way of customizing the Control Center, etc. Now 16 years later, you’re free to make most of the changes Android users have enjoyed (and teased us about) for over a decade. Embrace these updates and make it beautiful!</p>
<p>This part has the potential to be the most entertaining and engaging part of this whole reframing, at least for a certain kind of person. To avoid this post ballooning in size, I will leave you with a handful of general ideas and suggestions.</p>
<h3 id="app--widget-layout">App + Widget Layout</h3>
<p>After the purge, there are realistically only a handful of apps that you’ll use with any consistency. Put them in prominent places, like the dock or home screen, to minimize the number of taps they take to open. Leave the rest of the apps in the app tray.</p>
<p>App in app folders. Not my thing, but do you.</p>
<p>Consider using widgets for apps that don’t necessarily need to be opened to be useful; think of the Calendar, Weather, or Reminders widgets.</p>
<h3 id="focus-modes">Focus Modes</h3>
<p>I highly encourage you to experiment with  
<a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/108302" target="_blank">Focus Modes</a> as a way of emphasizing you when certain tools and apps should be used.</p>
<p>At the moment, I&rsquo;m experimenting with the following Focus Modes:</p>
<ul>
<li>📱 Default
<ul>
<li>Used for communication, music, exercise, with a few other commonly used tools like Authenticator or Google Maps</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>🌙 Sleep
<ul>
<li>Scheduled between 22:00 and 7:00 the next morning</li>
<li>Displays a few health and habit tracking widgets and nothing else</li>
<li>All notifications are disabled (except for my whitelist)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>💼 Work
<ul>
<li>Scheduled between 7:00 until 12:00 and from 13:00 to 17:00</li>
<li>Removes all communication apps, and replaces them with other work-related utilities</li>
<li>All notifications are disabled (except for my whitelist)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>✈️ Travel
<ul>
<li>Includes Flighty and other apps I use frequently when traveling like Google Translate, Uber, Currency Converter, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When done well, Focus Mode can make you feel like you have access to multiple different pocketknives with the flip of a switch.</p>
<h2 id="wrap-up">Wrap Up</h2>
<p>Phew, that was a lot! I feel I have much more to say about technology, news, social media, and many other topics that intersect with phones and the default relationship we develop with them, but I will save those thoughts for another time.</p>
<p>The process outlined above removed many apps that we probably open dozens of times a day, apps that distract us when we’re uncomfortable or bored, apps that anger us, and apps that, in turn, enable and encourage us to get angry at others. I won’t lie and claim that it’s easy or that there won’t be times you wish you had <em>that app</em> or wanted more information <em>right now</em> about a certain news event.</p>
<p>This approach may seem a little extreme, and it probably is. But that said, I know how much better I started feeling after wrestling back more and more of my attention, in large part because of many of the changes I just described. After some adjustment, I’d be a little surprised if you didn’t feel at least a little more focused. And, maybe, just maybe a little bit happier.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What's your humor setting Co-Pilot?</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 17:00:17 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-12-09-rr/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/copilot_humor_setting.jpg" alt="Meme from interstellar" width="1000">
&lt;p>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services,
&lt;a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt-plus" target="_blank">ChatGPT Plus&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" target="_blank">GitHub's Co-Pilot&lt;/a> but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &amp;ldquo;co-pilot&amp;rdquo; perfectly captures the &lt;em>current&lt;/em> relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing. As I began to type out &lt;code>url = &amp;quot;https://&lt;/code>, Co-Pilot generated a suggestion that I could accept by hitting tab. At this point, it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter what the URL was so I accepted the suggestion. Any guesses what the URL was for? What if I told you it was for a YouTube video?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/copilot_humor_setting.jpg" alt="Meme from interstellar" width="1000">
<p>As it currently stands, I pay for two AI services,  
<a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt-plus" target="_blank">ChatGPT Plus</a> and  
<a href="https://github.com/features/copilot" target="_blank">GitHub's Co-Pilot</a> but this number will surely increase in the coming months and years. I think the term &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo; perfectly captures the <em>current</em> relationship; these are tools that help me automate some of the boring or tedious tasks while also acting as an assistant that I can use to bounce ideas off.</p>
<p>Recently, while working on a side project, I needed a real URL for some testing. As I began to type out <code>url = &quot;https://</code>, Co-Pilot generated a suggestion that I could accept by hitting tab. At this point, it didn&rsquo;t matter what the URL was so I accepted the suggestion. Any guesses what the URL was for? What if I told you it was for a YouTube video?</p>
<p>If you guessed, Rick Astley&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ">&ldquo;Never Gonna Give You Up&rdquo; music video</a>, you would be correct. I got  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rickrolling" target="_blank">rickrolled</a> by my Co-Pilot, damn!</p>
<hr>
<p>Without going into too much detail on how these Large Language Models (LLMs) work, it&rsquo;s important to know that these LLMs are trained on billions and billions of lines of text data from online sources including blogs, forums, and digitized books, just to name a few.  What this means is that a large fraction of all the entertaining, beautiful, mean, hopeful, hateful, weird and wonderful things we have collectively written, have been internalized by these LLMs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not a huge surprise that a URL generated by Co-Pilot would be one of the most famous internet memes. I would guess it&rsquo;s among the top 5 common URLs found in the &ldquo;wild&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This experience has once again highlighted that interacting with these LLMs - at least at this point in their development - is like interacting with a mirror of humanity. Training these large models on our collective knowledge has proven that, when concentrated in one entity like GPT4, it has the potential to reflect the vast spectrum of human behavior and culture, both the profound and the trivial.</p>
<p>As AI continues to evolve, the line between tool and collaborator will become increasingly blurred. Today, we might see AI as a &ldquo;co-pilot&rdquo;, but in the future, these systems could become more akin to partners in our creative and professional endeavors. Or perhaps AIs could dispense with the need for a human &ldquo;pilot&rdquo; altogether.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of the previous two paragraphs were completed for my by ChatGPT using the previous paragraphs as the prompt.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I will conclude by encouraging folks who create content - practically speaking, everyone - to think twice before spreading lies, hate, or any other less-than-flattering ideas that will eventually be picked up by future LLMs; we should strive to ensure the best version of humanity is captured in the future training data sets.</p>
<p>If  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning_from_human_feedback" target="_blank">reinforcement learning with human feedback</a> (RLHF) is like scolding a child who swears, then improving the training dataset is akin to not swearing in front of the child to begin with.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s not swear in front of the AI.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Giant Sequoia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:39:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-08-13-sequoia/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson&lt;/a> on &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_unsplash.jpg" alt=" A picture of a bark Giant Sequoia from a low angle." width="1000"></p>
<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@nilsynils?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Nils Rasmusson</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/oRPinlCTEbk?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>
<p>Forest fires bring death and destruction, yet they also catalyze the birth of new plant life. The fire clears the overcrowded underbrush to create space and opportunities for the next generation, a cycle necessary for the health of the forest. However, like so many things, the quantity matters. Too little fire and not enough space is created for the next generation, while on the other hand, too much fire and the entire forest burns down.</p>
<p>There are species of trees that thrive in this fiery environment, one such tree is the Giant Sequoia.</p>
<p>Giant Sequoias hold the record for the largest tree by volume, specifically  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/seki/learn/nature/largest-trees-in-world.htm" target="_blank">General Sherman</a> with a trunk volume of over 1,480 cubic meters (52,500 cubic feet). They can grow up to 85 meters (280 feet) tall, and their gorgeous red-brown bark can grow up to 60 centimeters (24 inches) thick. The thickness of their bark, and lack of flammable sap, make these mature Giant Sequoias resistant to most fires.</p>
<p>The reproductive process of the Giant Sequoia and forest fires are intimately linked. The cones of the Giant Sequoia are serotinous, meaning they require an external trigger — in this case, fire — to release their seeds. The heat of the raging forest fire causes these tightly sealed cones to dry out and open up, setting their seeds free. With the cleared forest floor and a fresh layer of nutrient-rich ash, these seeds have an opportunity to germinate and become the next generation of Giant Sequoias.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re up close to a mature Giant Sequoia, you can often see the scars of past fires. You might be comforted knowing their offspring may be nearby</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/sequoia_fire_art.jpg" alt=" A painting of the bark of a Giant Sequoia that looks like fire." width="500"></p>
<p>As I write this, I reflect on the ideas of resilience, adaptation, and creative destruction in the broadest sense. It&rsquo;s August 2023, and some tangible form of AI is already here. Are humans like the Giant Sequoias, ready to use this power to our advantage, and to grow and develop beyond our current capabilities? Or are we like the old and dying underbrush that is about to be burnt away to make way for a new form of life?</p>
<p>Or is my analogy being stretched too far? Either way, I can&rsquo;t help but feel a sense of uncertainty about the future, a mixture of both anxiety and excitement.</p>
<p>Our ancestors harnessed the power of fire and it has been the stuff of legend ever since. It unlocked even greater opportunities for humanity and fair to say that fire has been a net positive even factoring in its destructive nature <sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Artificial intelligence is humanity&rsquo;s newest fire! A fire that listens, speaks and creates. Some of the dangers of artificial intelligence are easy to imagine, more fake news and increased surveillance, while understanding the potential existential dangers requires a robust definition of intelligence and a basic understanding of  
<a href="https://www.alignmentforum.org/" target="_blank">the alignment problem</a>.</p>
<p>Just as the immediate dangers are easy to imagine and the truly catastrophic ones difficult to pin down, the same pattern holds for the benefits of AI. The immediate benefits of AI are here already, a personal tutorial at your fingertips and the ability to generate new content with a faction of the effort. The truly awesome changes are difficult to predict.</p>
<p>Innovations as large and sweeping as the harnessing of fire, the invention of the atomic bomb or the creation of artificial intelligence force humanity to adapt to them in fundamental ways. Will AI burn too hot and destroy the entire forest, including the mighty Giant Sequoias? Will it usher in a new era of growth and prosperity? Or will it be regulated in such a way that it&rsquo;s rendered useless?</p>
<p>Thirty years from now, we will likely know how this has played out but until then, prepare for change and try to have fun with it!</p>
<p><sup>1</sup>
One possible way that the harnessing of fire might lead to the extinction of life on Earth (a net negative) is via the nuclear bomb, the ultimate expression of fire.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>eskild.art: going live</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-07-30-art/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 21:44:57 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-07-30-art/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art&lt;/a> is now live!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have plenty of ideas on what this might morph into but for now, it&amp;rsquo;s simply a gallery.
Can you solve the riddle to view the image?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> 
<a href="https://eskild.art" target="_blank">eskild.art</a> is now live!</p>
<p>I have plenty of ideas on what this might morph into but for now, it&rsquo;s simply a gallery.
Can you solve the riddle to view the image?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>March 2023 Update</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-03-11-update/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 18:28:06 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2023-03-11-update/</guid><description>&lt;p>When this blog first launched in 2019, I decided the quickest and easiest way to get started was to use Squarespace. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I was wrong but as my desire for more control over the site grew, a change was needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Introducing
&lt;a href="https://www.eskild.blog" target="_blank">eskild.blog&lt;/a>, now built using
&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank">Hugo&lt;/a> and hosted on
&lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since I&amp;rsquo;m not quite ready to build my site from scratch, I figured using a static site generator would give me the control I wanted without the additional maintenance burden that comes with managing a full-fledged, dynamic website.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When this blog first launched in 2019, I decided the quickest and easiest way to get started was to use Squarespace. I don&rsquo;t think I was wrong but as my desire for more control over the site grew, a change was needed.</p>
<p>Introducing  
<a href="https://www.eskild.blog" target="_blank">eskild.blog</a>, now built using  
<a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank">Hugo</a> and hosted on  
<a href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages</a>.</p>
<p>Since I&rsquo;m not quite ready to build my site from scratch, I figured using a static site generator would give me the control I wanted without the additional maintenance burden that comes with managing a full-fledged, dynamic website.</p>
<p>There are plenty of great static site generators out there but Hugo appears to be both flexible and fast.</p>
<p>As for GitHub Pages, I fully expect to experiment with other hosting solutions but it&rsquo;s the simplest way to get started.</p>
<p>To me, this blog is a work-in-progress, and probably always will be.</p>
<p>Anyway, that&rsquo;s enough for now. Happy blogging.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Joshua Tree</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 15:09:04 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
&lt;p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)&lt;/a>.
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park&lt;/a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself &lt;sup>
&lt;a href="#references">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/joshua_tree_at_night.jpg" alt="Joshua Tree at night" width="1000">
<p>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_brevifolia" target="_blank">Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia)</a>.  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/jotr/index.htm" target="_blank">Joshua Tree National Park</a>, located two hours east of Los Angeles, is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.</p>
<p>Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy. By the end of the current century, we could see the range of these majestic trees reduced by 90%, ironically this might include the Joshua Tree National Park itself <sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>All living organisms – including humans of course – are highly dependent on their environment and other organisms for survival; the Joshua Tree is no different. For the Joshua Tree to reproduce, it requires a unique set of weather conditions, as well as assistance from a few local species.</p>
<p>First, the Joshua Tree requires a winter freeze and a timely spring rainfall. These conditions alone inhibit the tree, and many other desert plants, from blossoming every year.</p>
<p>Once the tree does blossom, the flowers are pollinated by a single species, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prodoxidae" target="_blank">yucca moth</a>. These two species have come to a mostly mutually beneficial relationship whereby, in exchange for pollinating the Joshua Tree flowers, the yucca moth is permitted to lay her eggs inside the flower ovary. Not only do the eggs benefit from some level of protection, but the larvae also feed on the Joshua Tree seeds when they eventually hatch.</p>
<p>If enough seeds remain, the next act, though still not fully understood by scientists, seems to depend on the assistance of desert rodents such as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-tailed_antelope_squirrel" target="_blank">white-tail antelope squirrel</a>. By storing the Joshua Tree seeds in nearby, underground caches – often under the shade and protection of other desert shrubs such as the Blackbush – these squirrels offer the Joshua tree an increased chance that their seeds will germinate <sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Even if all these conditions are met, the chances of a seed germinating and growing to adolescence are still quite slim. Factor in the changing climate and the potential need for the Joshua Tree species to migrate to more suitable environments, and it&rsquo;s no wonder that the outlook of these trees is unfortunately bleak.</p>
<p>As individuals, there are changes we can make to reduce the negative impacts of climate change and to improve the odds that the Joshua Tree makes it to the 22nd century. Yet given the scope of the problem, large-scale societal changes will need to be enacted, and enacted soon.</p>
<p>However, we can honor the Joshua Tree, yucca moth, and the other desert species by recognizing our reliance on the environment, on other species and on one another. Doing so might make us more compassionate and remind us that our “successes” and our “failures” are not entirely our own.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup> Waitman, B. A., et al. “Seed Dispersal and Seed Fate in Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia).” Journal of Arid Environments, vol. 81, 2012, pp. 1–8. Crossref, doi:10.1016/j.jaridenv.2011.12.012.
<br>
<sup>2</sup> Jones, Taylor and Goldrick, Sabrina,  
<a href="https://pdf.wildearthguardians.org/site/DocServer/Joshua_tree_petition.pdf?docID=16684" target="_blank">Petition to List the Joshua Tree (Yucca brevifolia) Under the Endangered Species Act</a>, 28 Sept 2015.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Southern Magnolia</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 15:07:29 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Photo by
&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="/images/southern_magnolia_flower.jpg" alt="White flower of Southern Maganolia" width="1000">
<p><sup>Photo by  
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@wanderlust612" target="_blank">Katelynn Ruffner</a></sup></p>
<p>We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building materials, such as the orange and pine trees respectively.</p>
<p>And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.</p>
<p>However, one characteristic of trees not often discussed is their astonishing aesthetic beauty.</p>
<p>One such tree commonly planted for its splendor is the Magnolia tree and in particular, the Southern Magnolia (Magnolia Grandiflora).</p>
<p>This gorgeous evergreen can grow up to 30 meters (~90 feet) tall with a canopy that can potentially grow just as wide. Beloved in part for their large, white fragrant flowers, these trees grow natively in the south-eastern United States but have been planted across the country due to their popularity.</p>
<p>Across southern California, there are streets lined, and parks filled with these wonderful shade trees. For instance, there sits an enormous Southern Magnolia in the main park in my mom’s hometown, and when I see it, it puts a smile on my face for no other reason than its size and beauty.</p>
<p>Growing up, what distinguished magnolias from other trees, was first and foremost their large, waxy, oval-shaped leaves. Sure, there are other trees with leaves as large or larger, consider the maple leaf, but I can’t think of another tree with leaves as thick or as hardy as those from the Southern Magnolia.</p>
<p>Even though it was one of just a few trees that I could identify as a child, it wasn’t until a few years ago that I started to appreciate their true beauty. It’s not only a beauty that is perceived through my eyes and other sense but also one that is understood more intrinsically.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Grandmother's Valencia Orange Tree</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 14:59:24 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/orange_tree_single.jpg" alt="A single orange dangling from its stem" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I catch a familiar scent of orange blossom as I walk around my neighborhood, a scent I can’t help but associate with spring and summer at my grandma’s house.&lt;/p>
&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/orange_tree_sky.jpg" alt="A view of the top of the orange tree and the blue sky" width="500">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spent nearly every childhood summer at her place, a reprieve from having spent the previous ten, much colder, months in northern Europe. Her orange tree represented the hot California sun, with oranges the color to match.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_single.jpg" alt="A single orange dangling from its stem" width="1000"></p>
<p>I catch a familiar scent of orange blossom as I walk around my neighborhood, a scent I can’t help but associate with spring and summer at my grandma’s house.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_sky.jpg" alt="A view of the top of the orange tree and the blue sky" width="500"></p>
<p>I spent nearly every childhood summer at her place, a reprieve from having spent the previous ten, much colder, months in northern Europe. Her orange tree represented the hot California sun, with oranges the color to match.</p>
<p>A tall glass of her hand-squeezed orange juice on a hot and dry summer day rejuvenates the body with every sweet and delightful sip. A sweeter or juicier orange simply does not exist.</p>
<p>This vibrant  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valencia_orange" target="_blank">Valencia Orange Tree</a> is a fixture of my grandma’s house, as much as her 70’s era wood-paneled eastern wall is to her living room. And I’m so grateful she hasn’t torn the tree out, the unfortunate trend of many southern California homeowners.</p>
<p>My grandma’s orange tree has dependably provided oranges – and at times, other grafted citruses – for over six decades and is still going strong. And my grandma has dependably provided for her family – in all the traditionally unromantic ways – for just as long and, at nearly 85, still does what she can.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/orange_tree_inside.jpg" alt="A view of the inside of the orange tree" width="500"></p>
<p>I am learning a lesson from my grandma and her orange tree. A lesson in dependability and what it means to provide for others without asking for anything in return.</p>
<p>Throughout my life, I have probably slept more nights at my grandma’s house than anywhere else. And although my grandma and I haven’t always seen eye to eye, she has always been ready to provide for those in need. It’s in her nature, just as it’s the nature of an orange tree to blossom in the spring and fruit oranges in the summer.</p>
<p>If and when I get to her age, I hope to look back on my life knowing I was as trustworthy and dependable. That I provided for those that I love without doing so out of some sense of obligation or as part of some formal transaction.</p>
<p>I’m grateful for all that she has done for everyone and for all the good memories her house and her tree have enabled.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 14:50:42 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/bristlecone_pine_unsplash.jpg" alt="A large bristlecone-pine on the side of a rocky hill" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;sup>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine in the White Mountains (CA) photo by
&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@stp_com" target="_blank">Tim Peterson&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scattered atop a few of the high mountains of California, Nevada and Utah, sits an extremely special tree, the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinus_longaeva" target="_blank">Great Basin Bristlecone Pine (Pinus longaeva)&lt;/a>. Rooted in rocky and dry soil, they grow slowly and in isolation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Widely considered one of the longest-lived sexually reproducing, non-clonal organisms on earth, their long lifecycle has been instrumental to the scientific community.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/bristlecone_pine_unsplash.jpg" alt="A large bristlecone-pine on the side of a rocky hill" width="1000"></p>
<p><sup>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine in the White Mountains (CA) photo by  
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@stp_com" target="_blank">Tim Peterson</a></sup></p>
<p>Scattered atop a few of the high mountains of California, Nevada and Utah, sits an extremely special tree, the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinus_longaeva" target="_blank">Great Basin Bristlecone Pine (Pinus longaeva)</a>. Rooted in rocky and dry soil, they grow slowly and in isolation.</p>
<p>Widely considered one of the longest-lived sexually reproducing, non-clonal organisms on earth, their long lifecycle has been instrumental to the scientific community.</p>
<p>Due to the long lifespan of individual trees, and how extraordinarily slow their dead wood decays, scientists have been able to construct a continuous tree-ring chronology. This is done by comparing tree-ring samples from several different trees, both dead and alive, with the current chronology dating back over 9000 years <sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/dendrochronology.jpg" alt="Diagram explaining how tree rings from different trees match up to create a timeline" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Constructing a continuous tree-ring chronology (see  
<a href="https://archaeologymuseum.ca/dendrochronology-tree-ring-dating/" target="_blank">Museum of Ontario Archaeology</a>)</sup></p>
<p>This process is known as  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dendrochronology" target="_blank">dendrochronology</a> and has been vital in helping us understand the changes in climate and atmospheric conditions through the years. These insights have also been used to  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiocarbon_dating#Calibration" target="_blank">recalibrate the C-14 radiocarbon</a> dating process, helping archaeologists more precisely sketch out the timeline of the past.</p>
<p>Many of the discoveries and insights have only been made in the past few decades. How many more secrets do these Bristlecone Pines hold? And now consider the countless other tree species and the lessons they have yet to impart.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/bristlecone_pine_twisting.jpg" alt="A twisted bristlecone-pine branch against a blue sky" width="350"></p>
<p>Getting to see these warped and distorted giants up close forced me to reflect on how much the human species has accomplished in the lifespan of just a single tree.</p>
<p>Take  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methuselah_%28tree%29" target="_blank">Methuselah</a>, for instance, the namesake of the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methuselah" target="_blank">longest-living biblical character</a> and a tree  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dating_the_Bible" target="_blank">older than the bible</a> itself. This particular tree is estimated to be around 4,850 years old and holds the record for the oldest living tree <sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>For scale, Methuselah had already begun taking root around the time the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Pyramid_of_Giza" target="_blank">Great Pyramids of Giza</a> were being constructed, when the human population is estimated to be less than 27 million the world over. Just pause for a moment to consider how much the planet has changed and how far we have come as a species in that time<sup> 
<a href="#references">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Some might argue that the incredible progress we’ve made thus far will invariably continue while others argue that nothing in the past few centuries has fundamentally changed and point to all the problems in the world as evidence.</p>
<p>From my perspective, we have made immense and undeniable progress in the sciences and technology, and in the strengths of our institutions which attempt to embody our values and ideals. But if the past few years have demonstrated anything, it’s that we have much work to do.</p>
<p>We are living in a unique moment in history, at the elbow of an exponential curve of progress and abundance, but it’s important to remember that our actions and decisions today will be felt far into the future.</p>
<p>We might do well to take a lesson from these ancient sentinels, a species that has traded speed for longevity.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup>
Miller, Leonard. “Dendrochronology.” <em>The Ancient Bristlecone Pine</em>,  
<a href="http://www.sonic.net/bristlecone/dendro.html" target="_blank">www.sonic.net/bristlecone/dendro.html</a>.</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
Brown PhD, Peter. “RMTRR OLDLIST.” <em>Rocky Mountain Tree-Ring Research</em>,  
<a href="http://www.rmtrr.org/oldlist.htm" target="_blank">www.rmtrr.org/oldlist.htm</a>.</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>
McEvedy, Colin and Richard Jones, 1978, &ldquo;Atlas of World Population History,&rdquo; Facts on File, New York, pp. 342-351.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Big Berried Manzanita</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 14:44:05 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up
&lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail&lt;/a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_nps.jpg" alt="A single manzanita tree or large bush" width="1000"></p>
<p><sup>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)</sup></p>
<p>On the morning of Thanksgiving 2020, my roommate and I eagerly made our way up  
<a href="https://www.nps.gov/pinn/planyourvisit/maps.htm" target="_blank">Condor Gulch trail</a> to marvel at the rock formations this under-appreciated park was known for. And as the sun rose and the morning chill subsided, we took a break to remove some layers, when we realized we were in the presence of a tree neither of us had ever seen before.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/pinnacles_nps.jpg" alt="A view of the rock formations in Pinnacles National Park" width="1000"></p>
<p>It was the distinct, metallic-like, red bark that first drew our attention and our instant admiration.</p>
<p>I felt compelled to research this tree – what I would come to know as the  
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">Big Berried Manzanita (Arctostaphylos glauca)</a> – and this is exactly what I did when I got home.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_bark.jpg" alt="A close up of the metallic-looking bark of the manzanita tree" width="500"></p>
<p>Technically more of a large shrub than a tree, these striking evergreen plants are native to the chaparral regions of California and Baja California and have evolved an extraordinary robustness. They grow well in acidic soils, are resistant to heat, drought and cold, and can live up to 100 years<sup> 
<a href="#references">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>As their name suggests, the Big Berried Manzanitas are known for their relatively large, red berries and this is what distinguishes them from other manzanita species.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/manzanita_berries.jpg" alt="A close up of the red manzanita berries" width="500"></p>
<p><sup> 
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Arctostaphylos_glauca" target="_blank">“Arctostaphylos glauca“</a> by  
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Stan_Shebs" target="_blank">Stan Shebs</a> is licensed under  
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" target="_blank">CC BY 3.0</a></sup></p>
<p>The general term, manzanita, comes to us from the Spanish who thought the red berries resembled little red apples; the Spanish diminutive of &ldquo;manzana&rdquo; or apple.</p>
<p>These Big Berried Manzanita can reach heights of up to 6 meters or 20 feet tall, decorated with beautiful blue-green, oval leaves. Although I didn&rsquo;t bring my handy measuring tape with me, I was able to stand comfortably beneath the twisting branches to admire their bark.</p>
<p>A simply wonderful tree.</p>
<p>This trip reminded me of the importance of slowing down. And that the simple pleasures in life – the warmth of a campfire, the exhilaration of moving my body and the enjoyment of an honest conversation with a friend – are some of the best pleasures in life.</p>
<p>My roommate and I remain extremely grateful for the whole experience. We not only discovered the gorgeous manzanita tree, but as we sat to admire the beautiful pastel-colored rocks, we were fortunate enough to witness the majestic condor soar effortlessly overhead.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/soaring_condor_nps.jpg" alt="A soaring condor overhead" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Soaring Condor (NPS/Mason Cummings)</sup></p>
<p>I hope this series inspires you, dear reader, to get out and discover for yourself the wonders of our natural world. I will conclude with a quote from legendary naturalist John Muir<sup> 
<a href="#references">2</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The clearest way into the Universe is through a forest wilderness.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p><sup>1</sup>
Howard, Janet L. “Arctostaphylos Glauca.” Fire Effects Information System, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory, 1993,  
<a href="https://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html" target="_blank">www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arcglu/all.html</a> [broken link].</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
Muir, John, and Linnie Marsh Wolfe. <em>John of the Mountains: The Unpublished Journals of John Muir</em>. University of Wisconsin Press, Madison, 1979.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Introducing the Tree of the Month series</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 14:42:16 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">&lt;img src="https://www.eskild.blog/images/beautiful_woodland_path.jpg" alt="A beautiful woodland path" width="1000">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/images/beautiful_woodland_path.jpg" alt="A beautiful woodland path" width="1000"></p>
<p>Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.</p>
<p>To honor our important friends, once a month for the year 2021, I will share a post on a specific tree I find fascinating or have recently discovered myself. Some trees will be familiar to most, some trees might only be appreciated by scientists working closely with them. All of them will inspire awe and appreciation.</p>
<p>The explicit goals of this series are to introduce myself to more fascinating and beautiful trees while sharing my excitement with others. My wish is for trees, and our natural environment more broadly, to be looked upon with a set of fresh eyes, and fundamentally respected for all their forgotten benefits.</p>
<p>As far as I am aware, there exists not a tree in the universe besides here on Earth. As the species with the greatest ability to affect our surroundings, we ought to take better care of the trees, so they can take care of all of us.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2016 House of Representatives General Election: Campaign Finance Analysis</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-10-31-campaignfinance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 14:25:47 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-10-31-campaignfinance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>A Deep Dive into the 2016 House of Representatives General Election Campaign Finances&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This entire project started with one question: does the candidate who spends more money during a campaign end up winning that election?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However to avoid this project ballooning in scope and complexity, I had limit myself to the House of Representatives 2016 General Election. I choose to the House of Representatives because it has a larger number of concurrent elections, 435 compared to 50 in the Senate or one for President. I choose the 2016 election because, as of this writing, it is the most recently published election results on the Federal Election Commission&amp;rsquo;s (FEC)
&lt;a href="https://transition.fec.gov/pubrec/electionresults.shtml" target="_blank">website&lt;/a>. I also choose to limit my analysis to the General Election in order to avoid additional complexity arising from the variation in how each state runs their Primary Elections.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A Deep Dive into the 2016 House of Representatives General Election Campaign Finances</em></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>This entire project started with one question: does the candidate who spends more money during a campaign end up winning that election?</p>
<p>However to avoid this project ballooning in scope and complexity, I had limit myself to the House of Representatives 2016 General Election. I choose to the House of Representatives because it has a larger number of concurrent elections, 435 compared to 50 in the Senate or one for President. I choose the 2016 election because, as of this writing, it is the most recently published election results on the Federal Election Commission&rsquo;s (FEC)  
<a href="https://transition.fec.gov/pubrec/electionresults.shtml" target="_blank">website</a>. I also choose to limit my analysis to the General Election in order to avoid additional complexity arising from the variation in how each state runs their Primary Elections.</p>
<p>Lastly, I choose to limit my analysis to the finances related to the candidate&rsquo;s principal committee, more on this later.</p>
<p>All of the codes and graphs can found on  
<a href="https://github.com/iameskild/electionfinances.git" target="_blank">GitHub</a>. Feel free to download the data sets and perform your own analysis.</p>
<h2 id="defining-fec-terms-and-regulations">Defining FEC Terms and Regulations</h2>
<p>To make this analysis more understandable, some FEC terms need to be defined and some FEC regulations explained.</p>
<p>The FEC states that &ldquo;an individual running for federal office must register and file financial reports when he or she raises or spends more than $5,000 in contributions or expenditures.&rdquo; At which point &ldquo;all such candidates must register with a  
<a href="https://www.fec.gov/help-candidates-and-committees/registering-candidate/house-senate-president-candidate-registration/" target="_blank">Statement of Candidacy (Form 2)</a> and designate a principal campaign committee within 15 days of becoming a candidate as described.&rdquo;</p>
<p>For completeness a contribution (&ldquo;taking in receipts&rdquo;) is anything of value (money, goods, services or property) received by a political committee. Think fundraising.</p>
<p>And an expenditure (&ldquo;making disbursements&rdquo;) is a purchase, payment, distribution, loan, advance, deposit or gift of money or anything of value made for the purpose of influencing a federal election. Expenditures usually include paying for campaign headquarters, paying staff, running election ads and events, among many other things.</p>
<p>There are  
<a href="https://transition.fec.gov/info/contriblimitschart1516.pdf" target="_blank">limits</a> on how much a donor can give a candidate’s committee as well as whether or not the committee needs to itemize the donation. Donations need to be itemized if or once a donor gives more than $200, then referred to as an  
<a href="https://www.fec.gov/help-candidates-and-committees/filing-reports/individual-contributions/" target="_blank">itemized contribution</a>. Donations less than $200 are not required to be itemized and are known as unitemized contributions.</p>
<p>Each of these candidates should have a principal campaign committee ( 
<a href="https://www.fec.gov/help-candidates-and-committees/guides/?tab=candidates-and-their-authorized-committees" target="_blank">authorized committee</a>, or House committee ) which &ldquo;has been authorized by the candidate to accept contributions or makes expenditures on his or her behalf.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is these principal committees that provide the insight into how much money a candidate raised and spent over the course of an election.</p>
<p>There are of course  
<a href="https://www.fec.gov/campaign-finance-data/committee-type-code-descriptions/" target="_blank">other types of committees</a> that raise and spend money with the hope of influencing an election. Perhaps most notably are the independent expenditure-only committees, or more commonly known as Super PACs.  Like stated above, this analysis will solely focus on principal committees however I do have plans to analyze the finances of other committees in the future.</p>
<p>Lastly, during the course of a campaign, each principal committee is required to file periodic reports ( 
<a href="https://www.fec.gov/help-candidates-and-committees/forms/" target="_blank">FEC Form 3</a> ) detailing the total receipts (money, goods, etc. received) and the total disbursements (purchases, payments, etc. made) for the specified interval. These reports are filed quarterly, and leading up to both the primary and general elections.</p>
<p>Adding up the total receipts and the total disbursements for all reports filed will give us the grand total raised and spent over the course of the election.</p>
<h2 id="gathering-the-data">Gathering the Data</h2>
<p>The diagram below outlines, at a high-level, how the data was gathered and combined.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/data_flow.jpg" alt="Diagram 1: Gathering, Cleaning and Combining Data" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Diagram 1: Gathering, Cleaning and Combining Data</sup></p>
<p>The 2016 Election Results data set was downloaded as an excel spreadsheet from the FEC  
<a href="https://transition.fec.gov/pubrec/electionresults.shtml" target="_blank">website</a>. The relevant information was extracted and cleaned and is refered to as <code>results</code>.</p>
<p>The <code>results</code> data set contains the candidate IDs for each candidate which, along side the  
<a href="https://api.open.fec.gov/developers#/candidate" target="_blank">OpenFEC API candidate endpoint</a>, allows us to retrieve more information on each candidate, such as their respective principal committee ID.</p>
<p>Once the principal committee IDs are gathered, we can create a new data set which consists of the information from the <code>results</code> data set along with each candidate&rsquo;s respective principal committee ID, <code>pc</code>. This new data set is referred to as <code>results_pc</code>.</p>
<p>Now let&rsquo;s look at the percentage of candidates for whom we were able to find principal committee information.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/cands_pc_percent.jpg" alt="Chart 1: Percentage of Candidates with Principal Committees" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 1: Percentage of Candidates with Principal Committees</sup></p>
<p>There might be a few reasons why a candidate received general election votes but doesn&rsquo;t have a prinicpal committee.</p>
<p>I believe the most plausible explanation is that the candidate never filed a Statement of Candidacy because they never reached the $5000 threshold. The FEC then retroactively assigned a candidate ID because they appeared on the ballot.</p>
<p>There might have been candidates who filed a Statement of Candidacy but never authorized a principal committee. Or the candidate might have neglected to follow the FEC regulations and ran a campaign without ever notifying the FEC. I believe these last two explanations to be unlikely, and even more so if the candidate ended up winning the election.</p>
<p>Next, we can then use the  
<a href="https://api.open.fec.gov/developers#/financial" target="_blank">API financials endpoint</a> along with each principal committee ID to retrieve the details about each Form 3 filed by that principal committee during the 2016 election cycle.</p>
<p>We might expect to see a few candidates who did file a Statement of Candidacy but not report their spending to the FEC. The chart below indicates just this. This percentage can be no greater than the percentage of candidates who have principal committees.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/cands_form3_percent.jpg" alt="Chart 2: Percentage of Principal Committees that Filed FEC Form 3" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 2: Percentage of Principal Committees that Filed FEC Form 3</sup></p>
<p>Since the goal of this analysis is to determine whether spending more on a campaign results in winning the election, it is vital that we have information about a candidates spending during the campaign. Going forward, I think it is safe to assume that all the candidates that don&rsquo;t have principal committees or those who do but didn&rsquo;t report their spending to the FEC (Form 3) raised and spent less than $5000.</p>
<p>This assumption will allow us to continue the analysis without those candidates.</p>
<p>We now have a data set which contains information about the candidates, including their principal committee ID, and how they performed in the general election, referred to as <code>results_pc</code>.</p>
<p>We also have another data set which contains all the FEC Form 3 reports filed by each of the principal committees leading up to the general election, referred to as <code>financial_reports</code>. Because these principal committees are reporting their receipts and disbursements many times throughout the year, this data set contains multiple reports (rows) for each principal committee.</p>
<p>However we are only interested in the grand total raised and grand total spent for each principal committee so we can analyze them against the candidates general election results. To do this, I will create two new data sets, one that contains the grand totals for all columns related to receipts per principal committee and one that contains the grand total for all columns related to disbursements per principal committee. Each of these will then be separately combined with the <code>results_pc</code> data set to create two new data sets referred to as <code>results_pc_fr</code> (finances, raised) and <code>results_pc_fs</code> (finances, spent).</p>
<p>The columns from <code>financial_reports</code> that we are interested in are the listed below.</p>
<p><strong>Total Raised</strong> is the sum of the following categories:</p>
<ol>
<li>Individual Itemized Contributions</li>
<li>Individual Unitemized Contributions</li>
<li>Candidate Contributions</li>
<li>Political Party Committee Contributions</li>
<li>Other Political Committee Contributions</li>
<li>Transfers From Other Authorized Committees</li>
<li>Loans Made By Candidate</li>
<li>All Other Loans</li>
<li>Offsets To Operating Expenditures</li>
<li>Other Receipts</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Total Spent</strong> is the sum of the following categories:</p>
<ol>
<li>Operating Expenditures</li>
<li>Transfers To Other Authorized Committeees</li>
<li>Refunded Individual Contributions</li>
<li>Refunded Political Party Committee Contributions</li>
<li>Refunded Other Political Committee Contributions</li>
<li>Loan Repayments Candidate Loans</li>
<li>Loan Repayments Other Loans</li>
<li>Other Disbursements</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="analyzing-the-data">Analyzing the Data</h2>
<p>Before diving into calculating and analyzing correlations, let&rsquo;s get an idea of what percentage of candidates spent the most and also ended up winning their elections.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/spent_more_and_won.jpg" alt="Chart 3: Percentage of Candidates who Spent the Most and Won General Election" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 3: Percentage of Candidates who Spent the Most and Won General Election</sup></p>
<p>Although at this time it&rsquo;s difficult to make causal claims about whether spending more money during an election cycle has a direct impact on their chances of winning the election, it is clear that the candidates who spent the most money during the 2016 election cycle ended up winning the vast majority of the time. For 29 states, all of the candidates who spent more ended up winning and in 43 states, 80% of the candidates who spent more ended up winning.</p>
<p>There are likely many other confounding variables that haven&rsquo;t been taken into account but this chart is still fairly shocking and warrants further investigation.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s look at the correlation matrices for the numerical columns in <code>results_pc_fs</code> (disbursements).</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/corr_matrix_fs.jpg" alt="Chart 4: Correlation Matrix: Disbursements and General Election Results" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 4: Correlation Matrix: Disbursements and General Election Results</sup></p>
<p>It is clear that there is an extremely strong correlation (r=0.98) between &lsquo;Operating Expenditures&rsquo; and &lsquo;Total Disbursements&rsquo;, which might indicate that a majority of the money spent by the principal committee is on their operating expenses.</p>
<p>This makes sense since operating expenditures represents the vast majority of where the candidates would spent their money (from FEC glossary: &lsquo;day-to-day expenditures for items such as rent, overhead, administration, personnel, equipment, travel, advertising and fundraising&rsquo;).</p>
<p>There appears to be two columns, &lsquo;Operating Expenditures&rsquo; (r=0.37) and &lsquo;Total Disbursements&rsquo; (r=0.41), that have a moderate and positive correlation to &lsquo;General Votes&rsquo;. Let&rsquo;s explore scatterplots for both of these columns compared to the &lsquo;General Votes&rsquo;.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/disbursement_categories_vs_general_election_votes.jpg" alt="Chart 5: Disbursement Categories vs General Election Votes" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 5: Correlation Matrix: Disbursements and General Election Results</sup></p>
<p>By looking at the scatterplots for both &lsquo;Total Disbursements&rsquo; ($) versus &lsquo;General Votes&rsquo; (count) and &lsquo;Operating Expenditures&rsquo; ($) versus &lsquo;General Votes&rsquo; (count), the strength of their respective correlations is less clear. The general election winners, in general, appear to have spent more and received more votes and the reverse appears to be true for the general election losers.</p>
<p>Now let&rsquo;s take a look at which categories contribute the most to overall total disbursement.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/major_disbursements.jpg" alt="Chart 6: Major Disbursements" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 6: Major Disbursements</sup></p>
<p>The above chart makes it clear that operating expenditures account for the vast majority  disbursements (or spending). This is what we expected from such a high r-value above.</p>
<p>Next, let&rsquo;s look at the correlation matrices for the numerical columns in <code>results_pc_fr</code> (receipts).</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/corr_matrix_fr.jpg" alt="Chart 7: Correlation Matrix: Receipts and General Election Results" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 7: Correlation Matrix: Receipts and General Election Results</sup></p>
<p>Again, there appear to be a few receipt-related columns that are highly correlated to &lsquo;Total Receipts&rsquo;, namely, &lsquo;Individual Itemized Contributions&rsquo; (r=0.83), &lsquo;Individual Unitemized Contributions&rsquo; (r=0.45), &lsquo;Other Political Committee Contributions&rsquo; (r=0.69) and &lsquo;Transfers from Other Authorized Committees&rsquo; (r=0.5). These categories might account for where the majority of funding comes from, on average, for most candidates.</p>
<p>There appears to be two, or three columns that have a moderately positive correlation with &lsquo;General Votes&rsquo;, these would be &lsquo;Individual Itemized Contributions&rsquo; (r=0.39), &lsquo;Other Political Committee Contributions&rsquo; (r=0.54) and &lsquo;Total Receipts&rsquo; (r=0.43). The remaining columns have weak or no correlation to the general election votes.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/receipt_categories_vs_general_election_votes.jpg" alt="Chart 8: Receipts Categories vs General Election Votes" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 8: Receipts Categories vs General Election Votes</sup></p>
<p>Like the scatter plots generated for disbursement columns versus general votes, the scatter plots generated for these three receipt columns appear to have similar shapes. That is the winners of the general election, in general, receive more contributions than their opponents.</p>
<p>Lastly, let&rsquo;s explore where the majortiy of candidates contributions come from.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/campaignfinance/contributions_to_candidates.jpg" alt="Chart 9: Contributions to Candidates" width="500"></p>
<p><sup>Chart 9: Contributions to Candidates</sup></p>
<p>It appears that individual itemized contributions and other political committee contributions account for the majority of the funds raised (total receipts). This confirms the relatively high r-values seen for these two categories.</p>
<h2 id="wrap-up">Wrap up</h2>
<p>This analysis looked at the finances of the  Principal Committees  for (a majority of) the candidates who ran in the 2016 House of Representative elections. The question that was posed at the beginning of the analysis was, do the campaigns that spend the most money duing an election cycle end up winning the general election?</p>
<p>The answer appears to be yes. This doesn&rsquo;t mean that this is always the case or that the correlation is particularly strong but the analysis shows that there appears to be some kind of relationship money spent (and raised) and election results. There are surely other factors and confounding variables involved such as whether or not the candidate was an incumbent or what the political leaning of the district in question looks like, however this analysis ultimately sparks in me a desire to keep investigating this relationship.</p>
<p>There are a lot more questions and other avenues through which to analyze the affect money has on election results and I intend to explore those further in the months to come. Here are a few thoughts and ideas I would like to explore:</p>
<ul>
<li>Perform a more in depth analysis of the Primary Election</li>
<li>Perform a similar analysis for other years</li>
<li>Perform a similar analysis for Senate and Presidential races</li>
<li>Include other political committees in my analysis such as Joint Committees, PACs and Super PACs</li>
<li>Create a Machine Learning algorith to predict the winners for upcoming elections</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>3 Reasons to Visit the Eighth Continent, Madagascar</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 22:15:27 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is my attempt at writing at an exciting travel blog. I found writing this to be extremely fun and hope to write more about travel in the future.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You’ve been itching to see a part of the world most people haven’t and you’re hoping to jump into some good ol’ fashion adventure. You’re not alone feeling that most places on this planet have become overrun with tourists. For better or for worse, this trend is here to stay.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is my attempt at writing at an exciting travel blog. I found writing this to be extremely fun and hope to write more about travel in the future.</em></p>
<p>You’ve been itching to see a part of the world most people haven’t and you’re hoping to jump into some good ol’ fashion adventure. You’re not alone feeling that most places on this planet have become overrun with tourists. For better or for worse, this trend is here to stay.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/fresh_coconut.jpg" alt="a freshly opened coconut in front of the beach" width="500"></p>
<p>Although adventure usually conjures up images of exotic new lands or crazy experiences, the truth is that adventure is a deeply personal quest that can be had anywhere. It just requires an open-mind and a willingness to go with the flow.</p>
<p>As travel expert and author of  
<a href="https://rolfpotts.com/books/vagabonding/" target="_blank">Vagabonding</a>, Rolf Potts puts it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“More often than not, you’ll discover that ‘adventure’ is a decision after the fact - a way of deciphering an event or an experience that you can’t quite explain.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>However that being said, let me introduce you to Madagascar, the world’s eighth continent, an island like no other place on earth. If you’ve never considered Madagascar as a travel destination before, let me outline a few reasons why you definitely should.</p>
<h2 id="1-the-adventurous-landscape">#1 The Adventurous Landscape</h2>
<p>Red earth, lush rainforests, dry desserts, beautiful beaches, terraced rice and corn fields; the landscape here is simply intoxicating.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/red_earth_ocean.jpg" alt="a river delta showing the red earth emptying into the ocean" width="500"></p>
<p>Slightly larger than mainland France, at approximately 587,000 km<sup>2</sup> (or 227,000 mi<sup>2</sup>), this island nation is both large and diverse. It also ranks as the world’s fourth largest island.</p>
<p><em>For you curious cats, the larger islands are, in decreasing order: Greenland, New Guinea and Borneo. My sources tell me Australia is considered a continent.</em></p>
<p>The rawness of the land attracts anyone who loves outdoor adventure; you can hike, swim, snorkel or scuba dive, cycle, or simply sit and observe the country’s unique beauty. And, like most places, these activities are either free or very cheap. The exception being scuba diving.</p>
<p>Just pick an adventure.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/boat_at_sunset.jpg" alt="a single boat with the sun setting in the background" width="500"></p>
<p>Ride a rented bike up a hill for a view of the surrounding landscape while being greeted by locals along the way. “Salama!”</p>
<p>Snorkel or scuba dive off the southwest coast to catch a glimpse of one of the world’s largest barrier reefs (well, before it gets completely destroyed).</p>
<p><em>I splurged and got  
<a href="https://www.atimoo.com/en/" target="_blank">PADI certified</a> which consisted of 7 dives over 5 days. 5 out of 5 starfish, would do again.</em></p>
<p>Stroll through the city markets of Antsirabe taking in the sites and sounds of a bustling city while  munching on fresh baguette and drinking a cup of coffee that costs a combined 0.25USD.</p>
<p>Or if you’re lucky, watch enormous lightning bolts crack over nearby hills while above you the cloudless night sky reveals the Milky Way.</p>
<p>Whatever you do, definitely explore some of the amazing national parks. Visit Isalo National Park, dubbed The Grand Canyon of Madagascar by my park guide or chase cute Golden Bamboo lemurs through the rainforest in the Ranomafana National Park.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/valley_sky.jpg" alt="a view of the canyon known as the Grand Canyon of Madagascar" width="500"></p>
<p>This list wouldn’t be complete if it didn’t include sites such as the famous Avenue of the Baobabs, picturesque Nosy Be, or the two Tsingy National Park known for their jagged rocks formations and incredible endemic biodiversity.</p>
<p>Although getting around the island can be difficult - this goes for hired drivers or taking the taxi-brousse - don’t forget to enjoy the landscape as you drive through the country; you’re destination will undoubtedly reward you for your patience.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/taxi_brousse.jpg" alt="a taxi-brousse (bush taxi) being loaded for an upcoming trip" width="500"></p>
<h2 id="2-the-flora-and-fauna">#2 The Flora and Fauna</h2>
<p>Reason number two for visiting Madagascar is the incredible biodiversity; 90% of all plants and 70% of all animals are endemic to the island (found nowhere else in the world).</p>
<p>For instance, of the nine baobab tree species, six of them are only found in Madagascar, including the giant baobab.</p>
<p>Madagascar is also home of the lemur, more like over a hundred species of lemur. These monkey-like mammals are found in most of their National Parks and come in many varieties.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/baobab.jpg" alt="a unknown species of baobab" width="500"></p>
<p>There are twelve species of lemur in Ranomafana National Park alone, include the endemic small Golden Bamboo lemur (a matriarchal species). Or if you visit Isalo National Park, you can spot the famous ring-tailed lemur scaling cliffs with easy or simply hanging around the picnic area.</p>
<p><em>As a reminder, don’t feed wild animals. Though none of my park guides did, I have heard that some might in order to impress tourists.</em></p>
<p>Sadly, many lemur species and much of the biodiversity on the island is being threatened by deforestation and general human activity. Though the government is taking some action, many fear it’s not enough.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/lemurs.jpg" alt="two ring-tailed lemurs" width="500"></p>
<p>Often overlooked by tourists are the wonderful array of birds, reptiles, amphibians, flowers, and insects. And unlike Australia, most of the wildlife here isn’t out to kill you.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/chameleon.jpg" alt="a chameleon on the trunk of a small tree" width="500"></p>
<p><em>But who the hell wants to see insects?</em></p>
<p>One insect hard to miss is the non-venomous Golden Orb-Weaver spider. It’s truly a sight to behold, though perhaps from a distance. These nearly palm-sized spiders are found throughout the island and make you appreciate our elevated status in the food-web.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/spider_snaking.jpg" alt="a large spider ready to consume a recently trapped moth" width="500"></p>
<p>Animal-lover, tree-hugger, or not, Madagascar’s flora and fauna might not appear all the different at first glance, however upon closer examination,
you will find an alien world like nowhere else in the world.</p>
<h2 id="3-the-people">#3 The People</h2>
<p>Though a bit cliché, the most memorable experiences as a traveler often come from your interactions with new people, locals and other travelers alike.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/street_view.jpg" alt="a view of the street as people go about their daily business" width="500"></p>
<p>The Malagasy people - people from Madagascar - tend to be reserved but are generally very friendly. Be it with the person sitting next you on the bus, the receptionists at your hotel, or your National Park guide, you will be rewarded with more intimate knowledge of the country and the people if you can start a conversation.</p>
<p><em>Like most countries I have visited, rich or poor, the population is as interested in your country or culture as you might be in theirs. Ask respectful questions, answer theirs and make a friend in the process.</em></p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/mountain_house.jpg" alt="a small house with a steep, forested-mountain behind it" width="500"></p>
<p>One such example is that of Daha, a National Park guide in Ranomafana National Park, someone who cares greatly about the forest and animals. However, what made the interaction with him so much more engaging was the fact that he was just as curious about United States and Europe as I was in Madagascar.</p>
<p>Nicolas is another example of a local who, through sharing his experiences, added texture and context to the visit. He is a math student at the local university working at the Madagascar Underground hostel. He shared stories about the different tribes on the island and eventually through conversation explained how he took the initiative to coach soccer to the deaf students at his university.</p>
<p>What a badass!</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/lake_anosy.jpg" alt="a view of Lake Anosy from Haute Ville" width="500"></p>
<p>Then there are the other travelers you will meet.</p>
<p>Relative to its size, Madagascar receives very few tourists; fewer than 300,000 visited the island in 2016.</p>
<p>Although not a prime backpackers destination, those who do travel here, the Madagascar Underground hostel is a great place to begin your adventure.</p>
<p><em>I was told this is the only hostel on the island.</em></p>
<p>I meet a generous and entertaining Chinese man, who has been on the road for the past two years, at Madagascar Underground. We left the hostel together and ended up spending a week traveling together.</p>
<p>I was also lucky enough to spend time traveling with a Belgian woman who had been on the island volunteering for five months.  </p>
<p>And the last week I was on there, I befriended a Spanish woman who was leaving the island after spending the previous two years working as a dive instructor.</p>
<p align="center"><img src="/images/madagascar/bedroom_hut.jpg" alt="a small hut for sleeping and a view of the green valley behind it" width="500"></p>
<p>Interactions like these, along with many others, are the reason why traveling can be so much fun and exciting. And although you can meet interesting people and have such experiences anywhere on the planet, Madagascar felt different because of its remoteness and unique beauty.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Value of the KonMari Method</title><link>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-03-21-konmari/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 20:49:58 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.eskild.blog/posts/2019-03-21-konmari/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I recently discovered that Netflix has a series on
&lt;a href="https://konmari.com/" target="_blank">Marie Kondo’s&lt;/a> book &lt;em>The Life Changing Magic of Tidying - The Japanese Art of Decluttering and Organizing&lt;/em>. I guess I’m late to the party. No worry. From the book’s opening pages, Kondo writes, “A dramatic reorganization of the home causes correspondingly dramatic changes in lifestyle and perspective. It is life transforming.” This process is “life transforming” because it can, if taken seriously, drastically simplify your life, help you create your own “sacred space” and force you to identify what is truly important. I created a checklist to summarize the steps and outlined some lessons learned to share my personal experience however I’m going to assume whoever reads this post is aware of the KonMari method. If you are not, I strongly encourage you to read the book.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>I recently discovered that Netflix has a series on  
<a href="https://konmari.com/" target="_blank">Marie Kondo’s</a> book <em>The Life Changing Magic of Tidying - The Japanese Art of Decluttering and Organizing</em>. I guess I’m late to the party. No worry. From the book’s opening pages, Kondo writes, “A dramatic reorganization of the home causes correspondingly dramatic changes in lifestyle and perspective. It is life transforming.” This process is “life transforming” because it can, if taken seriously, drastically simplify your life, help you create your own “sacred space” and force you to identify what is truly important. I created a checklist to summarize the steps and outlined some lessons learned to share my personal experience however I’m going to assume whoever reads this post is aware of the KonMari method. If you are not, I strongly encourage you to read the book.</p>
<h2 id="why-bother-with-the-konmari-method">Why Bother with the KonMari Method?</h2>
<p>I read the book and completed her KonMari method in the late summer of 2017, however I was so focused on the methodology and trying to film the process that I missed the bigger picture; why was I doing all this work to begin with?</p>
<p>First, cleaning, collecting and organizing objects that are neither necessary nor fulfilling, is a waste of human potential, a waste of limited resources - time, money, and attention. And second, thoroughly minimizing and thoughtfully organizing your space empowers you to pursue activities you find meaningful. Some personal examples include a well organized kitchen which reduces the friction it takes to cook and a decluttered desk that calls me to sit down and write.</p>
<p>For a variety of reasons, in December 2018 I was determined to complete the KonMari method once more. By purging belongings that didn’t “spark joy” I took a critical step towards the lifestyle I desired. With fewer distractions, less clutter and an empowering environment, more of my limited resources can be focused on activities I truly value. Activities such as cooking and improving my writing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Reduce the complexity of life by eliminating the needless wants of life, and the labors of life reduce themselves.” - Edwin Way Teale, Naturalist</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="visualize-purge-and-tidy">Visualize, Purge and Tidy</h2>
<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
<p>The KonMari method is broken into three phases. I have labeled them Visualize, Purge and Tidy. The first step, Visualize, is for the reader to envision their ideal lifestyle and how their space and objects can support this new lifestyle. From page 38: “Before you start tidying, look at the lifestyle you aspire to and ask yourself, ‘Why do I want to tidy?’ when you find the answer you are ready to move on to the next step: examine what you own.”  I think most of us have an idea of the lifestyle we want nonetheless invest some serious effort answering this question before diving into the more tactile phases.</p>
<p>Moving on, the main focus of The Life Changing Magic of Tidying is on how to both tactically purge belongings that don’t “spark joy” and how to tidy and organize what’s left. This is where the checklist with accompanying “Pro Tips” comes in handy.</p>
<h3 id="the-checklist">The Checklist</h3>
<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="/files/konmari/konmari_checklists.pdf">Download a copy</a></p>
<h3 id="lessons-learned-and-personal-notes">Lessons Learned and Personal Notes</h3>
<p>As someone who has completed the KonMari method twice, both times in under 5 days, I will say it felt amazing to get it over and done with so quickly. However on the flip side, it’s exhausting and not everyone has the luxury of 5 consecutive days off. If this timeline is too short or unmanageable, I would strongly encourage completing a category or subcategory in one go. For instance “Clothes” could be completed in a weekend or going through “Magazines” could be the goal for an evening after work. Whatever timeline you settle on, complete it in the order prescribed.</p>
<p>For me, the “Miscellaneous” section was the most time consuming (and at times frustrating) section. This is partly because many objects seemingly fit into multiple subcategories and partly because it made me realize how many random items cluttered my small apartment: a V for Vendetta mask, a toy axe, a real axe. A partial solution is to leverage “Hobby subcategories.” The V for Vendetta mask and toy axe might fit nicely into a “Costume Party” subcategory while the real ax might be lumped in with either “Household Tools” or “Hiking Equipment”. It is far more manageable to have several smaller subcategories than one giant subcategory.</p>
<p>I also found that there were a handful of objects that didn’t “spark joy” but would be silly for me to toss out; my can opener comes to mind. In these instances, perhaps make a note of the item and see if there are objects of this type available that do indeed “spark joy”. Perhaps I just haven’t found the right can opener yet.</p>
<p>Lastly, I did deviate from the KonMari method in a few respects. I tried her folding method for several weeks but I found rolling my t-shirts to be much easier and saved just as much space; another benefit being that they are easier to pack when traveling. As for spare change, I hate change (of the metal coin variety). If I have spare change I will it leave in my car for parking meters, or leave it in a jar out of sight. I don’t carry a coin purse and I hate loose coins in my pockets.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I can’t remember where I came across Marie Kondo’s book but I’m extremely glad I did. It not only provided me with a straightforward process for minimizing junk and clearing space in my apartment (and my head) but helped open my eyes to benefits of a simpler and more intentional life. To summarize, stop toiling away incessantly reorganizing and collecting crap, perform the KonMari method then shift your focus to pursuing more valuable and engaging endeavors.</p>
<h3 id="postscript">postscript…</h3>
<p>There is much more I wanted to say about this book and the idea of “minimalism” in general however I had to stop here. I did want to share an amazing quote (shared by Tim Ferriss):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“In order to change skins, evolve into new cycles, I feel one has to learn to discard. If one changes internally, one should not continue to live with the same objects. They reflect one’s mind and psyche of yesterday. I throw away what has no dynamic, living use.” - Anais Nin, American-Cuban-French essayist</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>