<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Posts on eskild.blog</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on eskild.blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 15:11:54 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://eskild.blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Giant Sequioa</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/gs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 15:11:54 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/gs/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Joshua Tree</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 15:09:04 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-05-30-jt/</guid><description>The desert is an unlikely home for a tree, yet in the Mojave Desert of the US southwest, you will find a strange and sharply unique tree, straight from another planet, the Joshua Tree (Yucca Brevifolia). This desert celebrity – the namesake of the National Park two hours east of Los Angeles – is the perfect destination to appreciate these exceptional trees while they are still here.
Due to a variety of factors, which naturally includes a rapidly changing climate, the long-term survival of the Joshua Tree is in jeopardy.</description></item><item><title>The Southern Magnolia</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 15:07:29 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-04-30-sm/</guid><description>Photo by Katelynn Ruffner
We hear about the rainforest and are reminded of the important role trees play as a global carbon sink, breathing in carbon dioxide and releasing oxygen through a process known as photosynthesis. We have also known for millennia that some trees produce tasty fruit while others provide wonderful building material, such as the orange and pine tree respectively. And a stroll through any forest forces us to appreciate how vital trees are to their ecosystem.</description></item><item><title>My Grandmother's Valencia Orange Tree</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 14:59:24 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-03-31-gvo/</guid><description>I catch a familiar scent of orange blossom as I walk around my neighborhood, a scent I can’t help but associate with spring and summer at my grandma’s house.
I spent nearly every childhood summer at her place, a reprieve from having spent the previous ten, much colder, months in northern Europe. Her orange tree represented the hot California sun, with oranges the color to match.
A tall glass of her hand-squeezed orange juice on a hot and dry summer day rejuvenates the body with every sweet and delightful sip.</description></item><item><title>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 14:50:42 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-02-24-gbbp/</guid><description>The Great Basin Bristlecone Pine in the White Mountains (CA) photo by Tim Peterson
Scattered atop a few of the high mountains of California, Nevada and Utah, sits an extremely special tree, the Great Basin Bristlecone Pine (Pinus longaeva). Rooted in rocky and dry soil, they grow slowly and in isolation.
Widely considered one of the longest lived sexually reproducing, non-clonal organisms on earth, their long lifecycle has been instrumental to the scientific community.</description></item><item><title>The Big Berried Manzanita</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 14:44:05 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2021-01-29-bbm/</guid><description>Big Berried Manzanita (NPS)
Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.</description></item><item><title>Introducing the Tree of the Month series</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 14:42:16 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2020-12-31-totm/</guid><description>Trees are so vital to this planet and everything living on it but it seems this fact has been often overlooked or forgotten. Trees offer shelter for animals and beautiful building material for humans, they shade us in the summer and hold hillsides together, and the list goes on. However, trees (and other green plants) play a far more critical role; they are the lungs of our planet.
To honor our important friends, once a month for the year of 2021, I will share a post on a specific tree I find fascinating or have recently discovered myself.</description></item><item><title>2016 House of Representatives General Election: Campaign Finance Analysis</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-10-31-campaignfinance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 14:25:47 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-10-31-campaignfinance/</guid><description>A Deep Dive into the 2016 House of Representatives General Election Campaign Finances
Introduction This entire project started with one question: does the candidate who spends more money during a campaign end up winning that election?
However to avoid this project ballooning in scope and complexity, I had limit myself to the House of Representatives 2016 General Election. I choose to the House of Representatives because it has a larger number of concurrent elections, 435 compared to 50 in the Senate or one for President.</description></item><item><title>3 Reasons to Visit the Eighth Continent, Madagascar</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 22:15:27 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-05-05-mada/</guid><description>This is my attempt at writing at an exciting travel blog. I found writing this to be extremely fun and hope to write more about travel in the future.
You’ve been itching to see a part of the world most people haven’t and you’re hoping to jump into some good ol’ fashion adventure. You’re not alone feeling that most places on this planet have become overrun with tourists. For better or for worse, this trend is here to stay.</description></item><item><title>The Value of the KonMari Method</title><link>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-03-21-konmari/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 20:49:58 -0800</pubDate><guid>http://eskild.blog/posts/2019-03-21-konmari/</guid><description>Introduction I recently discovered that Netflix has a series on Marie Kondo’s book The Life Changing Magic of Tidying - The Japanese Art of Decluttering and Organizing. I guess I’m late to the party. No worry. From the book’s opening pages, Kondo writes, “A dramatic reorganization of the home causes correspondingly dramatic changes in lifestyle and perspective. It is life transforming.” This process is “life transforming” because it can, if taken seriously, drastically simplify your life, help you create your own “sacred space” and force you to identify what is truly important.</description></item></channel></rss>